<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cause of the innocent pleaded, his accusers pretended charge confvted, their unparallel'd actings, ungospel-like dealings, and unrighteous proceedings against their pastor, declared, or, Truth breaking forth, through the mist of clouds and slanders published by Samuel Bradley ...</title>
            <author>Bradley, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29112</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37453</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16958901</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16958901</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105462</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29112)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105462)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1610:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cause of the innocent pleaded, his accusers pretended charge confvted, their unparallel'd actings, ungospel-like dealings, and unrighteous proceedings against their pastor, declared, or, Truth breaking forth, through the mist of clouds and slanders published by Samuel Bradley ...</title>
                  <author>Bradley, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bradley, Samuel.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Discipline.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Clergy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105462:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Cauſe of the Innocent PLEADED, His Accuſers pretended Charge, CONFVTED; Their unparallel'd Actings, ungoſpel-like Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and unrighteous Proceedings againſt their Paſtor, DECLARED: OR, <hi>Truth breaking forth, through the Miſt of Clouds and Slanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed by <hi>Samuel Bradley;</hi> who is Afflicted, Rejected, Deſpiſed, Reproached; (yet a Friend to <hi>Zion</hi>) though troubled on every ſide, yet not Diſtreſſed; Perplexed, but not in Deſpair; Perſecuted, but not Forſaken, caſt down, but not Deſtroyed.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jer. 20.10.</hi>
                  </bibl> For I have heard the defaming of many, fear on every ſide; Report, ſay they, and we will report it.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa. 30.8, 9.</hi>
                  </bibl> Now, go write it before them in a Table, and note it in a Book, that it may be for the time to come, for ever and ever; That this is a Rebellious People; lying Children, Children that will not hear the Law of the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 18.17.</hi>
                  </bibl> He that is firſt in his own cauſe, ſeemeth juſt, but his neighbour cometh and ſearcheth him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105462:2"/>
            <head>To all who inquire the way to <hi>Zion,</hi> with their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thitherward; we ſend greeting, ſaluting all ſuch as love our Lord Jeſus in ſincerity.</head>
            <p>THat which hath been the ingaging cauſe to move us to this work of publick view, is that Controverſie which hath for ſome months been between the Author herein mentioned, and ſome perſons diſſenting from him, whoſe actings have been not becoming the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus: It is the joy of our Souls, the Reports and Scandals that have been caſt upon the Author herein mentioned, is through Grace made to appear to be no more but Reports and Scandals, which tends to his Crown of Rejoycing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.11.</p>
            <p>A Catalogue of the Proceedings of theſe people, for whom this Servant of God hath laboured in the Goſpel, you have in this enſuing Diſcourſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, To the Reader; if thou wilt be found, who ever thou art, to do that which may pleaſe God, and not prejudice thy own peace, then look upon the Matters and Controverſies in <hi>Sion</hi> with Spiritual Eyes, that ſo thou mayeſt diſcern it, leſt thou like the Spider, turn all into poyſon; therefore for thy help remember theſe three things:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Remember God is alwayes, and at all times, in all places preſent; let this ſtir thee up to a ſerious conſideration of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Remember the judgement due to them which put e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil conſtruction upon good things, which call evil good, and good evil; which put light for darkneſs, and darkneſs for light; and ſweet for bitter, and bitter for ſweet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Remember the great account that every man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man muſt give for every mercy received, and for every evil thought, every idle word, every ſinful action which is done or acted by the Sons of men, at the great day of the Lord's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As touching the Author herein mentioned, it being
<pb facs="tcp:105462:2"/>our portion to have moſt intimate communion with him in the time of his exilement, we are emboldned to ſpeak ſo far as we have ſeen, or ſo far as the Lord hath given us light and knowledge in the things of God, and in his wayes: we have ſeen nothing in his Life and Converſation, but as doth become the Goſpel; though in times paſt he was caught in Satans ſnare, and God did ſuffer him to fall under ſin, not to his Condemnation, but for his Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation; for God will loſe none of his Jewels, <hi>for whom he loveth, he loveth to the end:</hi> And God did manifeſt a powerful repentance in his Soul, and made ſin the object of his loathing; and as is made manifeſt by <hi>John Glyde,</hi> and <hi>Benjamin Minzes,</hi> in their Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles written in the Authors behalf, in his Book intituled, <hi>The Afflicted and Retired Mans Meditations, concerning the Excellency of the Spirit,</hi> where they writ very eminently in the Vindication of the Author aforeſaid, telling us, <hi>They were Spectators of the work of Repentance wrought in his Soul:</hi> In the aforeſaid Epiſtle is declared, <hi>That his whole converſation is as it becomes the Goſpel,</hi> to the which we do refer the Reader.</p>
            <p>The manifeſtation thereof is ſo great, that all the ſins he hath committed, and all the Devils in Hell, all the men upon Earth, profeſſors and prophane, are never able to verifie to the contrary. This we write not to applaud the Creature, but rather to promote the honour of the Creator, becauſe God hath born a teſtimony to the truth of it, as they themſelves have confeſſed; witneſs their Letter of Recommendation, wherein they ſay, <hi>The Lord hath made him inſtrumental to draw them out of the Pit of Darkneſs, and to bring them into the Glorious Liberty of the Sons of God:</hi> This is his <hi>Crown of Rejoycing,</hi> though they ſince have made it a time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, for want of a Spirit of love, and a ſound mind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We are not only Spectators of his Holy Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but alſo of his ſore Affliction, and great oppreſſion which he hath undergone by them, for whom he hath travelled in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; it being a work the Lord hath caſt into our hands, to ſtand up for his ſupport, under his oppreſſion, inflicted upon him by God for good ends, beſt known to himſelf, but inſtrumental by them on whom the travel of his Soul hath been ſpent; the thoughts of theſe things doth cauſe us for to tremble, to conſider the ungoſpel-like dealings which they have made uſe of to throw down their Paſtor and Brother in Chriſt, from that Center
<pb facs="tcp:105462:3"/>where the Lord did place him. A brief Catalogue take as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in theſe ſhort Particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They ſay aſide the Rules of Chriſt, and make uſe of their own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They reproach him before they reprove him, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Rule of Chriſt, or of his Apoſtle <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They charged him with ſin, but never proved it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> They Condemned him without any Tryal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> They ſay, <hi>they caſt him out,</hi> but never ſet a day apart to ſeek the Lords aſſiſtance in matters of ſo weighty concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and broke their promiſe which they made to one of us, to forbear their proceedings till the next Meeting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> They ſend Copies of his Accuſation to the Churches, and by no means he that was concerned therein muſt ſee it. And that which is matter of great lamentation, is, that one of theſe perſons, whoſe name is unto the pretended Charge, ſaid to <hi>N. C.</hi> a few dayes before the Breach, <hi>That he did judge</hi> S. B. <hi>had as much of the Spirit of God as any man in</hi> England: And yet proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>In this enſuing Diſcourſe, by the Author himſelf, you may ſee their work made manifeſt, and then you may determine whether it hath the Impreſſion of God, yea or nay, if you weigh it in the Ballance of the Sanctuary. Can any perſon prove, and ſay to this Author herein mentioned, all this time which report and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches have been ſpread abroad concerning him, <hi>This thou haſt done.</hi> If there had been any miſcarriage in him, where is the Spiritual-minded man, who according to the Rule of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, given in <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. that ever came to reſtore him with the Spirit of Meekneſs? This we may fear, that Love is wanting, or elſe the number of the Faithful is but few; And may it not be ſaid (concerning thoſe unparallel'd Proceedings of theſe Perſons) as it was in the beginning concerning the Woman, <hi>She takes of the Serpent, and the man received of the Woman, and ſo it ſpread over all man-kind;</hi> ſo now, the Woman takes from the ſurmiſing Spirit, which is of the Serpent, and ſhe delivers to the man, he ſpreads it abroad to the Churches, and this was the Original of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding againſt their Paſtor; but we have a Proverb in <hi>England,</hi> which is true in this caſe, That <hi>Conceit without receit, is plain deceit:</hi> We would leave with you, in the Love and Fear of the Lord, an
<pb facs="tcp:105462:3"/>Exhortation to Love, that great duty that is ſo little exerciſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the People of God.</p>
            <p>Did we live in Love, it would unite the hearts of the Faithful together; Love would cauſe God's Miniſters to ſtop the mouth of back-biters, reproachers, and ſcandalous perſons, which take up reports from report, without the knowledge of any thing that is reported; Oh let it be enough, that the Adverſary is ſmiting without, let not God's People ſmite within; its a ſymptom of the nearneſs of Chriſts approach, when fellow Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſhall ſmite one another; conſider the judgement due to ſuch; for it is too grievous to be born; for if we bite and devour one another, we ſhall be devoured one of another: for God hath ſaid, <hi>That if he kindle a fire in</hi> Gilgal, <hi>there ſhall be none found to quench it in the Houſe of</hi> Bethel; now therefore live in Love, then will the diviſions of <hi>Ruben</hi> ceaſe, that the Glory promiſed to the Churches and Members of Chriſt, may be given to them, which muſt not be looked for without a Reformation: therefore ſhake off the Raggs of Reproaching, and the Garments of Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting, and put on the Righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt, and come forth in the purity of the Spirit, which ſhall be the Prayers of them which are willing to ſuffer affliction for the Truth, Intereſt and Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, and have love to all that love the Lord Jeſus in ſincerity: We whoſe names are hereunto ſubſcribed, are for the moſt part eye and ear witneſſes to what is here expreſt, and therefore commend them to all wiſe-hearted people to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and remain the Aſſertors of Truth,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henry Tabor. Nicholas Clark. Thomas Roſe.</signed> 
               <dateline>The firſt day of <date>the 7th. month, 1664.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="charge">
            <pb facs="tcp:105462:4"/>
            <head>A COPY of the Pretended CHARGE againſt SAMUEL BRADLEY.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the Churches and faithful Brethren in Chriſt Jeſus, greeting.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved and longed for:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVE have at last as the Reſult which we hope the Lord hath brought upon our Spirits, reſolved to acquaint you with our Proceedings with <hi>Samuel Bradley,</hi> and the Reaſon of our ſo doing.</p>
            <p>Firſt, We do judge he ſtill lieth under the guilt of thoſe great and horrid crimes for which he was dealt with by his People.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As if all that were too little, he hath added, by ſeveral late and new Miſcarriages.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> A high diſorder, and therein a manifeſt breach of Truth, as he was an Overſeer in the Church of God, in bringing a Diſorderly Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon without the knowledge and againſt the Principle of the Church, and of the Truth it ſelf, to preach to them, and pray with them; and this is a compleate evil, eſpecially in him, ſo to run upon the Rule of Chriſt, ſo to hazard the Churches ſtability, which might have been invaded, by dropping ſome Doctrine as might have ſhaken the faith of ſome, and ſo manifeſtly to hazard the Churches Peace and Communion, eſpecially to bring in ſuch a perſon as he, contrary to the Advice given in the <hi>20th</hi> of the <hi>Acts,</hi> where the Elders are exhorted to feed the Church, and not to ruine it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> We have great cauſe to ſuſpect him very guilty of pernicious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns againſt the Saints; foraſmuch as he knew this Perſon he ſo brought in, to be a very dangerous wicked Perſon, and ſaying of him, he would never come into his company more; and now without publick ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction given by him, or taken from him, to bring him into the Church; and more then all this, to call out one Brother by Name, whom he knew zealous for the work of the Day, to pray in his preſence, as if he did on purpoſe lay in wait to catch what he could to anſwer him and others: this deeply and effectually perſwades us he could not be without great purpoſes to deal very treacherouſly with us.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> He is guilty of a very ſinful confederacy with this Enemie of the Lords, whom he hath ſingled out for his company, hugging and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing of him as a Brother, a friend that ſaw it, when he brought him
<pb facs="tcp:105462:4"/>into the Congregation; and ſince is a great frequenter of his Houſe and Company, as if it were a ſmall thing to wrap himſelf up in all his Iniquities, and ſo to draw upon himſelf the Vengeance due to ſuch vile tranſgreſſions, contrary expreſly to the Lords Commands, <hi>Say not a confederacy;</hi> and, <hi>Have no fellowſhip,</hi> ſaith our Apoſtle, <hi>with unfruitful Works nor Workers of Darkneſs: When thou ſaweſt a Thief, thou conſenteſt with him,</hi> Pſal. <hi>50.</hi> and that which is more conſiderable, one of his preſent Abettors and Adherents told us he did ſo to ſave his own ſelf: and hath hereby ſtained the Glory of Chriſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached the glorious footſteps of this Anoynted King, in which he hath eminently triumphed over his Enemies in theſe latter dayes, more than many, if not any in this day; and in which alſo he hath given the lye to his own Vows and Proteſtation in the ſight of God, That he hated and abhorred the thoughts of looking toward much ſelf with aſſociating with ſuch perſons, and yet now tell a Brother he was ſorry for what of that kinde he had ſpoken.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> He ſtands guilty of opening the Nakedneſs and Dealings in the Secrets of the Church in his publique Preachings, and this hath been frequent; being deſired by two Brethren to forbear ſuch Paſſages, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how diſhonourable they were to God, and grievous to them, he ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engaged never to do the like again; nevertheleſs at the very next Meeting he had of his own appointing, of which he had two or three a week, beſides the Church-Mettings, did publickly declare that his Church ſtopped his Mouth, ſo that he durſt not for diſpleaſing them preach thoſe Truths he would.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> He is guilty of ſuch raſh Paſſion and Spiritual Pride in his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages towards us in conviction and diſtinction, one to vindicate a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous tranſgreſſor that was to be dealt with in the Church, charged a Siſter with a lye in the face of the Church, and afterward to cover his evil made it a miſtake; to juſtifie the wicked and to condemn the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, both are in an abomination to the Lord; the firſt is, but few weeks but ſome or other would meet with their woundings and burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; and ſometimes meet with Repulſes in their Addreſſes to him, they muſt not teach their Elder; ſometimes he ſcorned to be taught his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by any Member in the Congregation; and ſometimes he would incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs them with fained Flatteries and Repentances, and yet in the mean time fly out into thoſe foul breaking parts, that indeed he was become a Burden to us: Alſo of ſome of thoſe petty things, we have alſo at large to be brought forth, if deſired by any. And if you adde to all this, his
<pb facs="tcp:105462:5"/>carriage while we were dealing with him; at one time breaking out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to very wicked reviling and contempt, as, He had brought up a Bird to pick out his Eyes, a Brother that then ſpake, Black-mouth, Foul-mouth, ſaid he had ſpit the Devil all day. And at another time vilely ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed at the Work of the Lord, being acquainted he ſhould be cut off, ſcoffingly ſaid, It would be cut and dried by and by. And as a further Evidence of his Hardneſs and Implacableneſs under all, when it was told him he was cut off, he makes that the time of his liberty, as he ſaid to ſome preſent with him, Now he had his liberty to go and preach the Goſpel unto the world: And gives out that he is wronged, and yet he hath made his Appeal to the Churches, and cannot be heard; and now makes his Appeal to God, and queſtions not but in a Twelvemonth he ſhall make Us and the Churches to know their Evil.</p>
            <p>This being but a brief Copy of thoſe many grand evils for which our Brethren before and now have cut him off, and caſt him out for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the fleſh: And ſo now bear our Teſtimony againſt all his evil, and all his Adherents; and ſet our Hands to the Truth of it.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Brothers.</head>
               <item>Glyde.</item>
               <item>Minzes.</item>
               <item>Johnſon.</item>
               <item>Morlie.</item>
               <item>Bentlie <hi>Senior.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hackney.</item>
               <item>Cook.</item>
               <item>Potter.</item>
               <item>Jones.</item>
               <item>Lane.</item>
               <item>Green.</item>
               <item>Aſton.</item>
               <item>Bentlie <hi>Junior.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Siſters.</head>
               <item>Abigail Fich.</item>
               <item>Mary Hackney.</item>
               <item>Elizabeth Hackney.</item>
               <item>Anne Bear.</item>
               <item>Elizabeth Haten.</item>
               <item>Gibbes.</item>
               <item>Laurence.</item>
               <item>Winter.</item>
               <item>Potter.</item>
               <item>Stirrup.</item>
               <item>Ellengray.</item>
               <item>Grove.</item>
               <item>Bentlie.</item>
               <item>Scales.</item>
               <item>Robinſon.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Reader may take notice, That <hi>Robert Bentlie</hi> Junior, whoſe name is ſet down to this pretended Charge, did declare to <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Roſe,</hi> That he did never ſet his hand to any ſuch thing: So that what may this be called but plain deceit? and it is abominable not onely in the ſight of the Lord, but good men alſo, and a ſin puniſhable by the Judge; to counterfeit a mans name, and bring him in as a Witneſs to their pretended Charge, when he was in no capacity ſo to be, as being then no Member of the Church. A farther Diſcovery of their Uncharitable Proceedings followeth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105462:5"/>
            <head>A brief Account of the Ungoſpel-like Dealings, and Unrighteous Proceedings of <hi>John Glyde, Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min Minzes, John Johnſon,</hi> and the reſt of the Diſſenting Members with them, manifeſted againſt their Paſtour, <hi>Samuel Bradley,</hi> as followeth.</head>
            <p>UPon the 5th day of the 5th month, 1663. at a Brothers houſe, namely <hi>John Glyde,</hi> was the Church meet, and continued all that day with one accord, preaching the Word, and in Prayer, yea, Breaking of Bread with gladneſs and ſingleneſs of heart, and praiſing of God; at the cloſe of the day, a Letter of Recommendation was read, in order to ſend me forth to preach the Goſpel; and the Letter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing read, they with one conſent aſſented, and immediately ſigned the ſame, and gave me up unto the Lord, his Work and Service, with endeared Manifeſtations of Love at our parting: The week following I took my journey, and at the evening of the ſame day, I entered upon the work; finding a door opened by the Lord after the Lord's Work was there accompliſhed, I travelled farther into the Country, where I found the Lord's harveſt to be very great, and did continue in the Work by night as well as by day, finding the People exceeding thirſty &amp; hungry after the Means of Grace; where much work for the Lord might have been done, had not falſe Reports &amp; Reproaches put a ſtop thereunto: After eight or nine dayes had been ſpent in this Service, quite contrary unto my own expectation, I was by providence returned back again to <hi>London,</hi> and at my return there was ſuch news preſented unto me, that I was ſtruck into ſome kind of amazement to hear of that diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that was in the Congregation, and of their Reſolutions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning me. The next day, being the firſt day of the week, they were reſolved to meet about me. Truly my ſoul was much grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, to conſider what a ſweet and heavenly Poſture I left them in about eight or nine dayes before, and to hear of ſuch a ſudden al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration; I being weary, riding very hard for to reach <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> that day, and hearing nothing of it before I came, I ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105462:6"/>down upon a bed, being over-whelmed in my ſpirit with grief and ſorrow, at laſt the Lord was pleaſed for to revive me again with theſe words, <hi>I will not leave thee comfortleſs;</hi> theſe words were ſet home with ſuch power through Grace, I was refreſhed and ſatisfied again, and ſet down my reſolution, by the help of the Lord, to go the day following, and make my appearance to the Church, that I might underſtand how things were: The firſt day being come, and the Church meeting at the place aforeſaid, where I left them in ſuch a ſweet harmonious poſture; they had begun before I had entered the meeting; after the firſt brother had end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his prayer, the ſecond began to ſpeak, <hi>Benjamin Minzes</hi> by name, and his way of ſpeaking was in ſuch a ſad railing reviling manner, as many can witneſs who were in the hearing thereof, that did admire at my patience, to hear my ſelf reviled at that rate. A little of his reviling Language is here repeated; <hi>That a hundred pounds was a great deal of money, to betray the People of God; and for a piece more he would do much; but let them go and do as</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das <hi>did, hang themſelves for their labour: and that he that ſhould joyn with a Trapan when he doth come to preach here, I would turn my back upon him and let him preach unto the walls. Benjamin Minzes,</hi> when the heat of his blood was over, did not go untold of it: to colour over his wickedneſs and deceit, makes this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply (thinking to ſhift it off, but it will not do) <hi>He did not name</hi> Sam. Bradly: This covering is too ſhort to cover over his evil; for beſides the teſtimony of his own conſcience, I have many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable arguments to prove it againſt him; but for the preſent I ſhall omit it.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Benjamin Minzes</hi> did in the bitterneſs of his ſpirit fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther declare openly unto all ſorts of People; <hi>Adviſing to ſerve them, as</hi> Samuel <hi>did</hi> Agag, <hi>hew them to pieces:</hi> Saying alſo, <hi>that they had power to cut off, and caſt out:</hi> Where we may plainly ſee, he ſtirred them up to cut off their Paſtor before they had given him ſo much as a hearing: and this is that they call their juſt dealing.</p>
            <p>And after <hi>J. G.</hi> had done preaching, <hi>B. Minzes,</hi> made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeech to the People, as if what he had ſaid to them, was not ſufficient to make them one with him in his wicked deſign, tells them, on purpoſe to make a Schiſm in the Church; and all this was done before they <hi>had read my Charge, or were come to my Tryal;</hi> he urges, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.23. before all the People there preſent; <hi>Abide
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105462:6"/>with me, &amp;c.</hi> wherein you may obſerve, <hi>David</hi> did intend to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from <hi>Doeg:</hi> So that it is plain, the deſign of <hi>Benjamin Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes</hi> was to make a Separation, whether there was cauſe for it or no: and for two or three hours together did I fit and hear my ſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled and falſely accuſed. When the meeting was ended, the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers diſmiſſed, and the Church retired, I began to make my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and notwithſtanding I was charged publickly, was willing for to bear it, and did hide their weakneſſes, hoping I might have been heard what I could ſay for my ſelf in private; no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er had I opened my mouth, had begun to utter my ſelf, but I was immediately intterrupted by the aforeſaid <hi>B. Menzes:</hi> and as he reviled me in publick, ſo he did revile me in private before the Church, calling of me, <hi>Retch, Thou Retch, thou ſhalt not ſpeak hear; and yet they have ſince commonly reported it abroad, I would not anſwer unto my Charge.</hi> When I perceived this uncivil carriage of the aforeſaid Perſon to me, who was his Paſtor, I ſaid, <hi>Benjamin Minzes, do you ſpeak as the Mouth of the Church, or being appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them ſo to do, to ſtop my mouth now it is my turn to anſwer to your falſe Accuſations in publick;</hi> He replies, <hi>Yea.</hi> And ſince I have enquired into the thing by ſome of the Members that could not in conſcience joyn with their unwarrantable Proceedings, but have found <hi>B. M.</hi> to be a lyar; for <hi>John Glyde</hi> was appointed to be the Mouth of the Church; wherein we may ſee the forwardneſs of this perſon to oppoſe me when he was not called thereunto, on purpoſe to carry on his own deſign: I did intreat that I might be heard; but of a ſudden there was a great noiſe, and a hurly-burly amongſt them, through the means of the uncivil Carriage of this poor man, in ſo much, that I was forced to be ſilent until ſilence was amongſt them: after a little ſilence, one of them ſpake unto me, and ſaid, <hi>That if I would hear my Charge, I ſhould be heard;</hi> To him I made this reply, that I was come there for that very end and purpoſe, by reaſon I did hear of a great ſtirr there was about me, and now am come to hear what is the matter; and ſince my coming, I have been highly charged by <hi>B. M.</hi> with heinous things, yea, ſuch things that my ſoul abhors, and I am now going, if you will have but ſo much patience, as let me be heard, to make my reply in private, to what I have been charged in publick, which is but a reaſonable thing; With that there was great confuſion again, ſome for it, and ſome againſt it; to the grief of my ſoul do
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105462:7"/>I relate it, with that I ſtood ſtill, till I had an opportunity to ſpeak, and then delivered my ſelf as follows.</p>
            <p>Friends, The Heathens abhor ſuch Proceedings as theſe are, inſtancing the ſayings of <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> John 7.51. <hi>Doth our Law judge any man before it heareth him?</hi> I have been judged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by <hi>B. M. to be a Trappan, and have,</hi> as he did tell the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>received Money for the ſame.</hi> But I am not ſenſible of any ſuch thing; and know he cannot prove what he hath ſaid, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let me ſpeak to clear my ſelf, for the Glory of God is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in this Matter: before I had done uttering my ſelf, I was again interrupted, and there was much confuſion. Again, I wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted till I could get another opportunity to utter my mind unto them, though much ado I had for to obtain it, but had it at laſt; I did plainly tell them, Their preſent work was to hear what I had for to ſay in order to what was charged upon me by <hi>B. M.</hi> but if they were reſolved not ſo to do, but juſtifie him in his evils, and diſorderly walking, and ſo become diſorderly walkers themſelves; I declared unto them what ever they did, I muſt walk according to the Rule of Chriſt preſcribed by him to us to walk by (though they would not.) After all this, I finding confuſion, diſtractions and diſorders abounding more and more amongſt them, and no likelyhood of being heard at all by them, which was my due as a Chriſtian, and much more my due as to that ſpecial relation in which I was related unto them (namely as their Paſtor) though not ſo uſed by them, as may be evidently ſeen.</p>
            <p>The next opportunity I had, I did in the Name and Fear of the Lord, (1.) Declare unto them their Evils, both in the matter and manner of their proceedings, with the aggravation of their ſin. Likewiſe after I had ſo done, <hi>I did in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt withdraw from them as diſorderly Perſons, not walking after the Order of the Goſpel, or Traditions that we have received of the Servants of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Theſ. 3.6. After I had ſo done, in as ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn a manner as I could, conſidering the great oppoſition I met with; and after I had declared my withdrawment from them, came a Brother to me (<hi>John Glyde</hi> by name) and he told me, <hi>That if I would come and hear my Charge I might;</hi> My anſwer to him was, <hi>I have pronounced the Sentence of Withdrawment in the Name of our Lord Jeſus,</hi> and I could not now, leaſt I ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Lord; you having broken the Righteous Rules of Our
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105462:7"/>Lord, and have put me out of a capacity of having any thing to do with you, till I ſee manifeſt Repentance; and as I was going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, ſome of them fell upbraiding of me, that they were reſelved for to caſt me out; I being informed of their Intentions or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations before, I made this Reply to them, I did know that it was ready cut and dryed; my meaning was, that it was ready done to their hands: and this is one of the Particulars they have added to fill up their charge, and other things that I ſhall reply to when I come to them, by the help of the Lord. Theſe Proceedings of theirs did much trouble me, my Bowels yerning to them as a Father, after thoſe few that could not in Conſcience joyn with them in their proceedings, being ſo abominable in the ſight of God and good men, to charge and condemn their Paſtor, and after they had ſo done, not ſuffering (as we have ſaid) him to plead for himſelf. And after we were gone, hearing of their deſperate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate proceedings, in making ſpeedy work of it, as if they were greedy of their deſign, to do as they called it, <hi>cut off their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor,</hi> though if they had fightly underſtood themſelves, was in no capacity ſo to do, being Perſons under dealing themſelves, and withdrawn from, for diſorderly walking, and yet to run ſo raſhly to work, never ſo much as ſetting a part a ſolemn day of Faſting and Prayer in Order thereunto, nor uſe any means in the leaſt for my return, if they could have proved I had fallen in what I had done, but contrary to Covenant engagements, and beſides a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular promiſe they had made to a brother there preſent; (that could not agree unto their deſign as warrantable in the ſight of the Lord) Their Promiſe was to him, <hi>to refer their work till the next time of meeting;</hi> And yet notwithſtanding, did proceed for all this to their inhumane Act with all expedition, and to run with ſtrong reſolutions to deal with, and caſt out, all thoſe that in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience could not joyn with them, And ſo continued walking con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to any Law of God or Juſtice in the World: Their conſtant proceedings to commit ſin by way of addition, adding one ſin upon the back of another, did oblige me, in love to their poor Souls, to write them a Letter of Admonition, and it was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſent them, and preſented unto them upon the next firſt day after they had committed their great folly that was acted to their Paſtor. A true Coppy, word forword, is as followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:105462:8"/>
            <head>To <hi>John Glyde, Benjamin Minzes, John Johnſon,</hi> and the reſt of the diſſenting Members with them.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IN the Name and Fear of the Lord God Everlaſting, I admoniſh you, as you will anſwer it at the great Day of the Lord, and at his appearing, that you will lay to heart your diſorderly proceedings againſt me your Elder and Paſtor, whom the Lord hath made to be your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to beget you to Chriſt; how is it that you are ſo ſoon forgetful of me, who once would, and not long ſince, have pulled out your ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eyes, and are not only now ready to pull out mine, but are ready to take away my Name and Life too, and that not for any juſt cauſe given you on my part, but by reaſon of ſome evil inſtruments amongſt you, who have made it their buſineſs to go up and down to hear and carry tales, who are buſie bodies,</hi> 1 Theſ. 3.11. <hi>of whom I warn you, that have made it their buſineſs to report; which have been as ſparks to kindle the fire, that is now alight about you, which would have been your wiſdom, as Church Officers, to have put it out, as being falſe fire, or elſe to have ſeen whether it was true; I cannot wonder enough, when I conſider your being called into the Liberty of the Sons of God, that you ſhould not underſtand your Duties as Members of Chriſt, who when any offend, you ought to tell them their fault between them and you, which is the Rule of Chriſt: So in the Law,</hi> Thou ſhalt not ſuffer ſin to be upon thy Brother; <hi>which you all knew, I was not ſo dealt withal with any of you: And whereas you proceed to Excommunication haſtily, without any proof made, or impartial ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination; how unlike the Primitive Example, ſee</hi> 1 Cor. 5.4. <hi>be you Judge: and then to ſlander me with things you never proved, and refuſe ſo to do. Oh! how contrary is this to the Mind of Chriſt, who ſpeak things they know not, nor whereof they affirme! I doubt not but my Innocency will appear before the Lord, when you ſhall not be able for to appear before him, unleſs you do all ſpeedily repent of this your wicked deed: Search, try, conſider in all the Book of God, or amongſt the Primitive Churches, or Proteſtants, whether you can find ſuch a preſident, to caſt out any Member without any examination or due proof made, much leſs to deal ſo with your Elder. Surely you have by this made the Enemy to blaſpheme, and the Churches a reproach and a by-word, and your ſelves to be looked upon by other Churches to be monſtrous. A true Property of a true Church, is, to have the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105462:8"/>of Chriſt truly adminiſtred: you have fallen ſhort of imitating the worſt of Churches, even</hi> Rome <hi>it ſelf, who doth not excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate without proof and contempt; and do you blame the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>for doing thus? Let me ſay to you in the words of the Apoſtle,</hi> Who art thou that ſayeſt, thou ſhalt not do thus and thus, and doſt the ſame? <hi>Oh! remember the ſad account you will give for break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Church of which you were Members, under the pretence of Scandal; for which unwarrantable dealing, I charge you in the Name of the Lord to make good your Allegations, and proceed as you ought to do if you can lay any thing to my Charge, I am ready to hear, or elſe I ſhall after two Admonitions more beſides this, proceed againſt you in a Church-way. I have no more, but expect to hear from you, and he Reſt,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Friend in Chirſt,<hi>Samuel Bradley.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>The 20th of the 5th month, 1663.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>But their obſtinacy was ſuch, they would not vouchſafe to look into it, one or ſome of them crying, <hi>Burn it;</hi> Another being more moderate then ſo, ſaid, <hi>Write on the back ſide, and ſend it him again.</hi> To leave them without excuſe in the Day of the Lord, I wrote another, and ſent it them as I did the former; the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger that carried it, ſtaid to hear them Preach, and hearing of them much upon the work of inviting ſinners unto Chriſt, burſt forth in much trouble of Spirit, ſaying words to this purpoſe, <hi>How can you invite ſinners in, and did caſt a poor ſinner out,</hi> (meaning their Paſtor) <hi>and never hear him what he could ſay for himſelf?</hi> and immediately preſented this Letter to them, as followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>A true Copy of the ſecond Letter of Admonition, ſent to <hi>John Glyde, Ben. Minzes, John Johnſon</hi> and the reſt.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IN the Name and fear of the Lord God, I ſend this Second Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition (and to warn you that you diſregard it not) as you will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it at the great day of the Lord's appearing: You with the reſt have done unbecoming the Goſpel, in throwing your ſelves out of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Order, who pretend Purity with Unity, while your ſelves ſuffer contrary walking amongſt you, even ſuch as is juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveable; it is to be feared you have thrown off your Goſpel-Order, that you may walk more diſorderly; it is the grief of my Soul to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105462:9"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:105462:9"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105462:10"/>think how it is with you, and how you will be able to give an account at the great Day, for making ſuch a Diſtraction in the Church of God; if you have any thing juſtly to reprove me of, I deſire to be dealt withal in a Church way; but if you will abide in your diſorder, as my dear Children, I warn you, for none can be more like-minded, or naturally care more for you than my ſelf; but if you will ſtill abide in your ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornneſs and wilfulneſs, you muſt expect but one admonition more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I declare to the Churches of Chriſt your ſtubbornneſs, and paſs a Goſpel-Sentence further upon you, in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is all at preſent from him, who earneſtly prayes to the Lord for you, and that he would be pleaſed for to diſcover unto you your Sin, and give you repentance for the ſame, ere it be too late.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>I reſt, your Elder which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires your good, <hi>Samuel Bradley.</hi>
                     </signed> 
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From my houſe,</hi> 
                        <date>27th of the 5th <hi>month,</hi> 1663.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>But the like obſtinacy appearing from them as before; I did notwithſtanding judge it my duty, to diſcharge my conſcience in the further proſecution of the Rule of our Lord Jeſus, ſent unto them the third time alſo; although they did not ſo deal with me, I was willing to expreſs good for evil, and ſo left it to the Lord, until we had an opportunity to preſent their Proceedings to the Churches, or ſuch as are competent Judges in this caſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>A true Copy ſent to <hi>John Glyde, Benjamin Minzes</hi> and <hi>John John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and the reſt of that Party.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>IN the Name of the great God Everlaſting, I ſend this Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition as the laſt to you, that you may expect; which if you refuſe, remember that according to the Command of Chriſt, you muſt be dealt withal by cenſure. What I have admoniſhed you of, hath been your diſorderly walking, and breach of covenant, and promiſe made, and ſuffering diſorderly perſons to walk amongſt you; I am apt to think that what you have done, is on purpoſe, that you might walk with more licenciouſneſs: and know that you will never be able to give an account of your breach made upon falſe ſuppoſed grounds: have you any real grounds? ſhew them; Truth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105462:10"/>is never afraid of the Light: men commonly hate the Light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their deeds are evil. As my dear Friends, once more, and the laſt, I warn you of your diſorder, before I proceed to reject you and give an account to other Churches, which when I have done, I am ſure will be done in a Goſpel-Order, and Way, that I dare ſtand by at the great Day. O that the Lord would ſhew you the evil of your way, before it be too late.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Friend in Chriſt, <hi>S. B.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This was rejected alſo: and hearing that ſome of them had falſely given out, that I would not hear my Charge when deſired, I went to <hi>J. Glyde,</hi> whom I did judge was the moſt moderate, and wiſeſt man amongſt them, deſiring of him that I might have a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of my Charge; and he promiſed me I ſhould, but could not have it then: at another ſeaſon I went unto him again, with an expectation of the accompliſhment of his promiſe; but he was not to this day ſo good as his word, though I did much intreat him for it: my intent only was but to reply thereunto, yet could not obtain my purpoſe: I did reſt contented, and bore with their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful terms, in ſaying I would not anſwer to it; and bleſſed be the Lord, he helped me to bear that burden, with others that hath been caſt upon me.</p>
            <p>After all this, my tender bowels ran forth ſtill to theſe poor ſouls, whom I had travelled for in the Goſpel; notwithſtanding all their unkind dealing with me, I made it my buſineſs ſtill (forbearing a further proceeding againſt them in a Goſpel-way) to make uſe of other means, endeavouring to bring it about, if poſſible I could, for to reclaim them from their preſent diſorders; I went to the perſon fore-mentioned, and ſaid, <hi>Brother</hi> Glyde, <hi>it is poſſible there have been ſome offences taken by Friends on your part, in my being in the company of</hi> E. R. <hi>you not knowing the grounds and reaſons why it was ſo to this day; it was not to the prejudice of any; and you have given an offence to the Lord on your part, in proceeding ſo raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not taking of the Rule of Chriſt with you, nor making that your Rule, for you to judge before you hear me ſpeak: Let us ſet a day apart, and ſeek the Lord together, or aſſunder, and make acknowledgement to God, and each other, of our particular failings &amp; offences, and humble our ſelves
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105462:11"/>in the ſight of the Lord, and be reconciled one to another.</hi> But this Propoſal was not accepted of; as though they were fully reſolved never to be reconciled more. I ſeeing all this, quietly gave my back to the Smiter, and have been holpen by the Lord to bear thoſe ſundry and innumerable Reports that have been given forth againſt me from that time to this; I being not willing to revenge my own Cauſe, but rather leave it to the Lord, knowing aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he will plead the Cauſe of the Innocent: for Wo is like to fall upon the heads of the ſcandalous Reporters, without they ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent.</p>
            <p>It hath been commonly reported, (yet, bleſſed be God, could never be proved) <hi>That I ſhould privately and cunningly carry on per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious deſignes againſt the Godly, and lay wait to inſnare them at their Meetings;</hi> though at the ſame time it can be proved I have been preaching of the Word at my own; and have made it my dayly Work, as many can witneſs, to pray for them. <hi>And for ſome ſeaſon ſome have made it their buſineſs to ſend Meſſengers and Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters up and down the Countrey, to render me odious, on purpoſe to make the Godly afraid of me; and this hath been done in all parts of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (reporting without proving) leaving a Charge up and down to the Churches, To ſhun me, and by no means give Entertainment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me:</hi> And as touching the pretended Charge they have ſpread, none could be ſuffered to copy it out, though deſired by ſuch as deſired to be ſatisfied in the Truth of the matter as well as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, fearing I ſhould come to a ſight of it: So that for a long ſeaſon together where-ever I have gone preaching the Word, I have been told they have both ſeen and read my Charge, as they called it; the like proceedings being not to be parallelled in any Age, That a Man muſt be judged, condemned, and defamed up and down the Nation, and never be ſuffered to have a ſight of his Charge.</p>
            <p>For more then a twelvemonth together have I groaned under this Burden, and upon the fifth of this preſent Month 64. by a ſtrange hand of Providence (as the Lord ſure would have it) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to any of thoſe who have proved my Accuſers, The Lord caſt me into <hi>Kent,</hi> to preach the Goſpel at a place called <hi>Aſhford,</hi> fifty odd miles from <hi>London,</hi> where a Brother did preſent this pretended Charge into my hand, with the names of the perſons concerned in the matter ſubſcribed.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:105462:11"/>
            <p> Thus all ſober-minded Perſons may ſee how their works have been the Works of Darkneſs, and that they have been afraid to bring them forth unto the Light, that they may be made manifeſt. Seeing the Lord hath brought to my view the thing I have ſo much deſired to ſee, which goeth under the Denomination of a Charge, I ſhall with all expedition fall upon the examination thereof, to try their ſtrong Reaſons, by which they do ſeem to prove <hi>Samuel Bradly</hi> to be as <hi>B. Minzes</hi> hath prated, <hi>Deotrephes</hi>-like: (3 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.10. <hi>Deotrephes who loveth to have the preheminence among them, received us not: I will remember his Deeds which he doth, prating a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us with malitious words; and not content therewith, neither doth he himſelf receive the Brethren, and forbids them that would, and caſteth them out of the Church:)</hi> He and the reſt of his Adherents have reported me through the Nation to be that, which (through Grace) neither he nor any elſe could ever prove, namely a <hi>Trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan;</hi> and 'tis very well known they have not been wanting to blaze abroad theſe following particulars, and in ſuch a way too, as by no means muſt it come to my hand whom it did moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern; which renders their Cauſe to be very bad, being fearful to bring it to tryal: And now it is come forth, contrary to their knowledge or expectation; to paſs by their <hi>nonſenſical,</hi> and to be feared, <hi>hypocritical</hi> Recantation, that hath of late been made by them; and ſome of their hands I finde ſubſcribed to this preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Charge, that were not at all concerned therein: What their end was, to do ſuch a ſinful action, I know not, unleſs it be to ſeek the favour of Men. In the ſaid Recantation they have mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably belied the Works of God, which their eyes have beheld; and now are not aſhamed to manifeſt themſelves Lyars, by their late proceedings, for to pleaſe the humours of ſome men, to ſay as they ſay, though it hath been manifeſtly proved to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as will hereafter appear by their own hand-Writing.</p>
            <p>The way I ſhall proceed to anſwer unto their pretended Charge, is,</p>
            <p>Firſt, To ſpeak unto the matter contained therein; and as to the manner how it was managed, I have in a brief way already expreſſed: But as touching the matter contained therein,</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall prove that which they call a Charge, to be none.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their pretended Charge to be a lye.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105462:12"/>
            <p> As to the firſt particular, In that which they call a Charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Samuel Bradly:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>We do judge he ſtill lieth under the guilt of thoſe great and horrid Crimes, for which he was dealt with by his People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To my great ſorrow and dayly grief of heart, there was a time ſome years paſt, that God did ſuffer me to fall, which was a means to bring me very low, and I hope will not be forgotten by me to my dying day: It doth to this day adminiſter great hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation in my ſoul, at every remembrance thereof; and lying low in the ſight of God, yea in ſecret; the Searcher of Hearts knows it to be true; and it doth cauſe me to bow down ſtill under the conſideration of my former tranſgreſſions, and the abuſe of Free Grace: after ſome ſeaſon of travel in the bitterneſs of my Soul, did the Lord gratiouſly manifeſt, in his Love and tender Compaſſion, a blotting out of my ſins for ever, by helping of me to ſuck out ſweetneſs in the Promiſes of Free Grace: I forbear to enlarge. This was not onely apprehended ſo to be by me, but the large Teſtimony of the Lords appearance to me ſince, hath been born witneſs unto in an eminent manner by theſe very peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who have now raked into my old ſores, and by their means are publiſhed through the Nation: They have now placed them in the front of their pretended Charge, thinking thereby to make their Cauſe appear the more righteous: Some may think that theſe perſons are hard put to it, to retreat back to failings done ſo long ago, to make a new War with their Paſtor again, after ſo many years of Peace: May not ſome ſay, Rather then fail to have our revenge on him, we will hit him on the old ſore, and deal with him upon the old ſcore? Seeing they cannot prove their Paſtor to be a <hi>Trappan,</hi> they will wheel about, and charge him with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing done in the year 58, or 59. What will a ſober-minded man ſay, when he comes to hear of this, if he may be heard ſpeak without prejudice? Theſe kinde of actings or proceedings, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover but little love, and the ſpirit by which they carry on their work, not as it becomes the Goſpel they make Profeſſion of; to cry out againſt all their former proceedings, and call them Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, to purchaſe to themſelves the favour of ſome People; yea, that which may be ſpoken to their further ſhame, is, Before they could purchaſe to themſelves the aforeſaid Enjoyments, namely, The Society of ſome, whoſe Names I forbear to expreſs
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105462:12"/>being not willing to bring them upon the publick Stage, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the preſent capacity they are in. Some of theſe poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures rather than they will be deprived of the credit of ſome of the Churches, they will deny their Faith and Baptiſm too, and go down into the Water again, thinking to make null their former Witneſs they bore unto Truth: Any that have the leaſt ſpirit of diſcerning may ſee that theſe <hi>Children,</hi> ſince they have flung themſelves out of the plain Rules of the Goſpel, and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe diſorderly ways, have run into ſuch a diſorder of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptizing, as never was heard of in any of the Churches of Chriſt in the Ages paſt: by theſe things they have made it appear that they are <hi>Children toſſed about with every wind of Doctrine,</hi> running from one diſorder to another: Where will they run next, if God in mercy do not put a ſtop thereunto?</p>
            <p>But to return from their Actions to their Expreſſions: Say they <hi>[We judge:]</hi> Here we ſee the ignorant blinde zeal of theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that take upon them to charge and judge their Paſtor name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>John Johnſon, Roger Morly, Robert Bently, Samuel Hackney, William Green, John Aſten, Jeoffry Lane,</hi> and divers others; I ſay again, Here is made manifeſt the ignorance and blindneſs of theſe perſons, to bear witneſs againſt their Paſtor, <hi>That he was under the guilt of horrid Crimes,</hi> yet never had a true knowledge of any thing that might have ſo much as a tendencie to ſuch a thing, but by hear-ſay: for thoſe things they ſeem to charge me with, were long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any of theſe were a ſeparated People: now if theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ons were in a fit capacity to be baptized, as they call it, again, or received as Members anew, let ſuch as are truly ſpiritual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine: And let their new Paſtor conſider, That thoſe that have uſed their old Paſtor ſo baſely, to report him up and down the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as a Committer of horrid Crimes, when they know no ſuch thing of him; let I ſay their new Paſtor fear and look well about him, leſt theſe people ſerve him in the like kinde: O that thoſe aforeſaid, and the reſt of their Companions had taken it into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, That when they drew up this Charge againſt their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, whether they did not let ſlip the following Scripture out of their mindes, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.21, 22. <hi>If the wicked ſhall turn from all his ſins that he hath committed, and keep all my Statutes, and do that which is lawful and right, he ſhall ſurely live, he ſhall not die; all his tranſgreſſions that he hath committed, they ſhall not be mentioned unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:105462:13"/> 1. They may do well to conſider, becauſe they take upon them to be Judges in ſuch weighty matters, That it is a work which doth not belong to them, it being too high for them: for it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belongs to Chriſt himſelf; <hi>The Father hath committed all Judgement to the Son,</hi> John 5.22. yet theſe men will adventure to judge their Paſtor, when <hi>Paul,</hi> the Noble Apoſtle of the Gentiles, ſaid, <hi>What have I to do to judge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By this act they have proved themſelves to be under the breach of the Law; and in ſo doing have made work for Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: not at all regarding the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Speak not evil one of another: he that speaketh evil of his Brother, and judgeth his Brother, ſpeaketh evil of the Law, and judgeth the Law.</hi> O that they would judge no longer, but rather conſider the Judge ſtands at the door, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.9. O how dare they ſay now, they judge their Paſtor guilty of thoſe Crimes which they themſelves have cleared him of, long ago! witneſs their Letters of Vindication, beſides that of Recommendation they ſent him forth to preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel by; as you may ſee in the concluſion of my <hi>Reply</hi> to their pretended <hi>Charge:</hi> Beſides the Teſtimony of my own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and alſo theirs, I am cleared from being guilty of thoſe heinous Crimes they have charged upon me. So much by way of anſwer to their firſt <hi>Particular.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Par. <hi>As if all that were too little, he hath added ſeveral late and new Miſcarriages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This depending upon what comes after, I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore examine into the matter of their Particulars, and make my Reply unto them diſtinctly.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Par. <hi>Firſt, A high diſorder, and therein a manifeſt breach of Truth, as he was an Over-ſeer in the Church of God, in bringing in of a diſorderly perſon, without the knowledge, and againſt the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Church, and of the Truth it ſelf, to Preach to them, and Pray with them; and this is a compleat evil, eſpecially in him ſo to run upon the Rule of Chriſt; ſo to hazard the Churches ſtability, which might have been invaded by dropping ſome Doctrine as might have ſhaken the Faith of ſome, and ſo manifeſlly to hazard the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Peace and Communion, eſpecially to bring in ſuch a Perſon as he, contrary to the advice given in the twentieth of the</hi> Acts, <hi>where the Elders are exhorted to feed the Church, and not to ruine it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For my diſtinct Anſwer hereunto, I ſhall draw this up into ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Particulars.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:105462:13"/>
            <p> To the firſt branch I give this Anſwer; Let all ſober minded perſons determine how this can be juſt and right in the ſight of God, to charge me with that which was not, nor can ever be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: If ſo, then how can it be a manifeſt breach of Truth, as they ſay, when it is altogether falſe what they aſſert? Theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may do very well to call in their pretended Charge again, till they have got their witneſſes ready to prove what they ſay; for they very well know, that no Accuſation can be received againſt an Elder, but by the mouth of two or three Witneſſes; ſo that they may ſee what they have ſaid amounts yet to no Charge; and let them take notice, that while they ſeem to plead for the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the Church, they may do well to practiſe the Principle of Love; then they will not dare to ſlander their Neighbour, much leſs their Paſtor, as they have done: They may alſo take notice, that it was ſo far from being a diſorder, that it remains for them to prove it was any diſorder at all.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Whereas they aſſert, <hi>I brought him in to Pray as well as to Preach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I have to ſay, That it is a plain untruth, and as falſe as the former; here you may plainly ſee how they contradict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and prove themſelves Lyars. In the firſt Particular they ſay, though very falſly, <hi>I brought him in to Preach and Pray;</hi> when I am able to prove he never prayed at all, with or amongſt them; and yet in their ſecond Particular they blaze it abroad in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>That I called out a Brother by Name to pray, whom I know,</hi> as they ſay, <hi>was zealous for the work of the day:</hi> For ever hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter let them hold their peace, and live in ſilence, till every one have learn'd to ſpeak the Truth to his Neighbour: They very well knew, as I ſaid before, he never prayed amongſt them; and with what confidence they could write theſe untruths abroad unto the Churches, to render me odious, and ſuſcribe with their Names thereunto, I know not?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They ſay, <hi>This is a Compleat Evil in him, to run upon the Rules of Chriſt, ſo to hazard the Churches Stability.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer; They had done very well, if they had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved what they ſay, for we have nothing but their bare word for what they affirm; they ſay, <hi>It is a compleat evil;</hi> they had wrought like workmen indeed, if they had proved that I brought him into the Meeting, then they might have had ſome ground for what they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105462:14"/>ſay. But as for their word, <hi>Compleat Evil,</hi> ſure it wants an Expoſitor: for I never read in the Scriptures, that Evil was a compleat thing. This being not in their power for to prove, it is very evident I did not break or come ſhort of any Rule of the Churches, nor hazard the Churches Stability. But as for their word, <hi>Run upon the Rule of Chriſt,</hi> it is ſuch a learned or unlearned Expreſſion, that I do not conceive what they mean by it: So their pretended Charge is made null and void, that it is plainly ſeen, they have made a great noiſe in the Nation about me for a thing of nought. Repent for this your folly and great iniquity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> And whereas they ſay, <hi>Which might be invaded by dropping of ſome Doctrine which might have ſhaken the Faith of ſome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer; Here they aſſert they know not what; <hi>Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> ſignifies to ſet with violence and force upon a People: as they of old <hi>invaded the Land,</hi> 1 Sam. 23.27.</p>
            <p>It alſo imports to cut in pieces: and the Invaders of God's People were the <hi>Amalakites;</hi> as they may ſee in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.1. the <hi>Moabites,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 30.20. the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 38.18. the <hi>Ammonites, Aſſyrians, Midianites,</hi> and others: now here they have plainly made manifeſt their Charge to be nonſenſical, as if I would bring a man to cut or break my Church in pieces, and offer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to them. Again their folly doth further appear, that inſtead of bringing evidence for what they ſay againſt their Paſtor, which in juſtice ought to have been done, they ſay by way of ſuppoſition, <hi>Such a thing might have been.</hi> Is this fair dealing, to cry a man up and down the Nation for a <hi>Trapan,</hi> and turn him out of their affections, and make ſtrong endeavours to caſt him out of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affections of all good people too, in as much as in them lies, by caſting ſcandals upon him, without bringing of him to a lawful Tryal, or ſuffer him to be heard ſpeak for himſelf? ſurely no <hi>Court</hi> of Judicature will judge, or Jury be ſo baſe as to caſt a man for an abſolute Offendor, upon a Suppoſition: and what, would theſe men offer ſo to do, that profeſs to judge for God! Pray let me ask them by what Law do they <hi>Judge, Caſt</hi> and <hi>Condemn</hi> me for ſuch a Perſon as hath been commonly reported, but yet never could be proved? I dare affirm not by God's Law: conſider if this be right in the ſight of God, let thoſe who are my Adverſaries be judge; and how the Peace of the <hi>Church</hi> could be hazarded, as theſe men tell the Nation, I know not, when he that ſpoke, brought
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105462:14"/>no other Doctrine, then what they had before received; and thoſe few that were at the hearing thereof, by their own confeſſion, were refreſhed by what was delivered; that to the truly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>Chriſtian</hi> it doth appear, the Peace of the <hi>Church</hi> was ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inlarged then hazarded, That ſo their pretended <hi>Charge</hi> is made manifeſt to be none at all.</p>
            <p>The fifth thing I obſerve in the ſecond Particular, is, as they ſay, <hi>Eſpecially to bring in ſuch a Perſon as he, contrary to the advice given in</hi> Acts 20. <hi>where the Elders are exhorted to feed the Church, and not to ruine it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> As to their Tautology, I paſt it by, becauſe it cannot be proved that I brought him in to Preach; and as touching the Apoſtles advice, <hi>We are to feed the Church:</hi> Theſe Perſons them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do witneſs for me, that I ſo did, namely, <hi>Feed the Flock of Our Lord Jeſus,</hi> not only in their Letter they did write to me when I was a Priſoner for the ſame; But now alſo in their fifth Particular of this pretended Charge, they ſay, <hi>I made it my work to Preach three times a week, beſides the Church Meetings.</hi> But as touching their laſt Term, I am altogether a ſtranger to, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>as to ruine the Church:</hi> for as the Lord ſpoke by the Prophet to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Oh</hi> Iſrael, <hi>thou haſt deſtroyed thy ſelf;</hi> So do I ſay, If they be deſtroyed or ruined, it is done by themſelves; It is plainly ſeen, that Lyes, Surmiſings and Suppoſitions, is their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Particular ſtuffed with, in this their pretended Charge; that it plainly appears to ſuch as are plain-hearted, to be no Charge, but a heap of falſhoods.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Par. <hi>We have great cauſe to ſuſpect him very guilty of pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Deſigns againſt the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This hath its dependance upon the former; they do not ſay they charge me, but <hi>ſuſpect me,</hi> and withall, <hi>they would have us believe they have great cauſe ſo to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is as falſe as the former; for all men will believe this, that if they could have ſhown either great or little cauſe, they would not have ſpared me, but without all doubt have brought it forth. They talk of <hi>Pernicious Deſigns, that I am guilty of againſt the Saints,</hi> but nothing do they prove, or can they.</p>
            <p>The Reader may take notice that ſince this pretended Charge was hatched and patched together, it is ſomewhat above a twelve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>month; And what, is not one <hi>Pernitious Deſign</hi> diſcovered all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105462:15"/>this time? Surely it is apprehended by ſuch as have learned bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then to live in the prejudiced mind, or ſurmiſing Spirit; this Babe that hath been ſo long in the Womb of Conception, will prove an abortive at laſt. As touching the Perſon whom they ſo much mention again and again, whom they call <hi>Dangerous and Wicked;</hi> as to his former Proceedings I juſtifie not, but have ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther choſen to reprove them, what ever I have been thought on, and laboured to make it my buſineſs to reclaim him; but this I can truly ſay, no perſon whatſoever, in City or Countrey, all the time of my ſociety with him, (which was not of any long ſtanding) I do declare and affirm had not any wrong done to them by my knowledge, for which I have great peace, though my ſufferings have been very great, as to ſome other things in this Particular; being one thing rehearſed over again, I do apprehend it a ſuperfluous thing to make a ſecond reply thereunto.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As touching my Calling, <hi>a Brother by Name, who</hi> they ſay, <hi>was zealous for the work of the day, as if he lay in wait on purpoſe to catch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I Anſwer, As touching his zeal for the work of the day; it did not very much appear, foraſmuch as he did not appear in the work, till the day was near an end. The Searcher of Hearts knows my innocency in this thing, that I had no intent, but what was agreeable unto the Mind of God; and by this time one would have thought theſe perſons might have ſeen great cauſe to have been deeply humbled, for their evil thoughts they had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Paſtor; I do now appeal to the moſt fearful, and the moſt jealous Perſon amongſt them; whether to this day they have been harmed in the leaſt by me? If not, as I am very confident they cannot ſay they have, what Reaſon is there that <hi>S. Bradley</hi> ſhould ſtill remain charged upon this account to this day, ſeeing there can be nothing of this nature proved againſt him, but lie under ſcandal by reaſon of their unwarrantable groundleſs fears, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſings and ſuppoſitions? I ſay unto theſe perſons, Is it not high time that their poor oppreſſed Paſtor ſhould be ſet free, and at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from this bondage that he hath been expoſed to by their means for a Twelvemonth together, and more? O when will their Goal-delivery come! They will do very well to try their ſpirits; for it may be ſaid unto them by me, as it was ſaid by our Lord Jeſus to his Diſciples, <hi>You know not what spirit you are of.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105462:15"/>
            <p> Whereas they ſay, <hi>As if he did on purpoſe lie in wait to catch:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, If we take it in their own ſenſe, which will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be the worſt, it is but <hi>as if he did,</hi> they themſelves cannot ſay, He abſolutely did <hi>lie in wait to catch:</hi> If they had dealt fairly and honeſtly by me, they had done well to have ſet down ſome of the particular things that were acted in a treacherous way, and not keep people in the dark, and act towards me as if I were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring ſome horrid things againſt them, when there was no ſuch thing by me thought on: Theſe kind of proceedings ſavour not of a good Spirit, to rob their Paſtor of his good name, and all ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered but from their evil perſwaſions: Would not the Heathen abhor ſuch dealings, if they ſhould hear of them? I wonder they were not aſhamed to ſet their hands to ſuch things, to declare their weakneſs to the Churches abroad.</p>
            <p>And whereas they ſay, <hi>This doth deeply and effectually perſwade them he could not be without very great purpoſe to deal very treacherouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with them:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This amounts to no <hi>Charge</hi> all this while: by their own ſpeech they cannot poſitively prove it, but are perſwaded it is ſo: what proof is this to the caſe in hand? by the ſame Rule, if this may carry it, I may ſay that theſe people that have reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me cauſleſly and and groundleſly, are turned Robbers in the High Way: how ſo? I ſuppoſe ſo; or (to ſpeak in their own words) <hi>I am perſwaded it is ſo:</hi> Surely this kinde of proof, which to ſpeak truly is no proof, will not carry it here, nor in the day of the Lord. I pray obſerve, Theſe People have, as it were, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned their Paſtor at the Bar, and have writ and produced his <hi>Charge</hi> againſt him; the Evidence they produce to make good this their <hi>Charge,</hi> is, Suppoſition or Perſwaſion; now if Reaſon ſit Judge, do theſe men think to carry it againſt their Paſtor? ſurely nay: Then are not theſe men much to be blamed? and ought they not to mourn greatly for what they have done, in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the life of their Paſtors Reputation, and all upon a ſuppoſition, ſeeing what they have ſaid againſt him is not poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive? Then I muſt and ought in <hi>Conſcience</hi> to be acquitted and cleared of all thoſe ſcandalous Reproaches that have been and ſtill dayly are caſt upon me by this groundleſs means.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, all men of underſtanding may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105462:16"/>that <hi>S. B.</hi> is an Innocent perſon ſtill, and altogether clear from any guilt that is caſt upon him in this pretended <hi>Charge:</hi> and ſince it is brought to light, we finde they can prove no treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous dealing againſt the perſon aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Par. <hi>He is guilty of a very ſinful Confederacy with this Enemy of the Lord, whom he hath ſingled out for his Company.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, Here they have diſcovered both their Folly and Ignorance: A <hi>Confederacy</hi> doth imply a <hi>League</hi> or <hi>Agreement</hi> between perſons, as they in <hi>Act.</hi> 23.21. <hi>layed wait by way of confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy for Paul, to do him harm, and bound themſelves in an oath that they would neither eat nor drink till they had killed him;</hi> here is a <hi>Confederacy</hi> indeed: Is this their meaning that I am a <hi>Confederate</hi> with that Perſon, to do any of the People of God any harm? Had the Lord at any time left me to ſuch wickedneſs as this, I make no queſtion they would not have ſpared me a jot, but the Nation ſhould ſoon have had the knowledge of it: Truly theſe dark ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences will not much promote their Cauſe and unwarrantable Deſign, that for ſome time they have been endeavouring to keep up in the mindes of Good People; they have in ſo doing been building upon the ſand, and without all doubt their Building will tumble upon their own heads ere long. The Eagle-eyed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doth behold their ſumptuous Fabrick to tumble already: and though they have deſigned to throw down the Innocent, yet let them know, their ſurmiſing ſuppoſitions will never carry the day: for unleſs they come forth in down-right poſitive terms, they are not like to caſt me in open Court, but themſelves: for God will have <hi>Judgement and Juſtice to be executed ſpeedily;</hi> and they cannot charge me with any evil that I have acted with the perſon fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, to any of the tender Lambs of Chriſt, or any others</p>
            <p>Thus much may be expreſſed without the leaſt wrong to any of their perſons, That they are all guilty of many ſinful Lyes that they have forged againſt him who was their ſpiritual Paſtor; ſo that they are guilty of a ſinful compliance themſelves: for I prove them all confederated together to murder my good Name, and have cried me up through the Nation for a <hi>Trappan,</hi> when they can prove no ſuch thing; ſo that I may ſay of them as 'tis ſaid in <hi>Obadiah,</hi> verſ. 7. <hi>All you the men that were in League with me, in holy Covenant, yea, who were once at peace with me, have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105462:16"/>me, and</hi> by your lying falſehoods and ſurmiſing pretended <hi>Charge</hi> you have ſent abroad, <hi>have prevailed againſt me;</hi> yea, you have eaten Bread with me at the Table of the Lord, (O that I could write it with Tears of Blood!) yet ye <hi>have laid a wound un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me;</hi> and it is to be feared for theſe things <hi>there is no underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in you.</hi> That in the mean time they are charging of me with Confederacy, though groundleſly, they are proved to their faces to be great Confederates themſelves, in caſting dirt in the face of the Innocent by ſcandalous Reports, and all this is done under pretence of Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>As to the latter part of this Particular, I have anſwered alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and therefore need ſay no more to it. They are guilty of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Tautologies in this pretended <hi>Charge,</hi> whether it be from weakneſs or wilfulneſs, I ſhall not ſit Judge in the caſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Whom he has ſingled out for his Company, hugging and embracing him as a Brother: A Friend that ſaw it when he brought him into the Congregation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> And what harm was there in all this, that I was in his company? which thing I have anſwered to already: Let me ask theſe forward perſons, which are ſo nimble to condemn the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Innocent, before he had either a fair Hearing, or a fair Tryal: and what they did, muſt be with all expedition too; that is to ſay, Reproached, charged, judged and condemned, and all in leſs then one days time; and what was done, was behind my back too; fearing to refer their Work till the very next Meeting, leſt they ſhould not obtain their purpoſe, as one of their Party was heard to ſay, namely <hi>Benjamin Minzes,</hi> which can be proved to his face, he expreſſing himſelf in theſe terms, <hi>If we do it not now, we ſhall not do it at all;</hi> which plainly demonſtrates they had a Deſign to carry on: ſure it was not a good one, that they ſhould fear to miſs of their purpoſe in the accompliſhment of it. But to return to the queſtion: Was my being in his company, as I ſaid before, prejudicial to any from that day to this? were it convenient to write what I have to ſay in this caſe, I could eaſily make it appear I did well in ſo doing: They have now produced one Witneſs to a thing I deny not; however, it is very well done to prove what they ſay, and if they had ſo done in every Particular of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Charge,</hi> they had ſaved me the labour of writing an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; Then I ſhould have cried out <hi>Guilty,</hi> without any more
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105462:17"/>ado; and had they ſo done all along, it had redownded much unto their Credit and Reputation: But now they have cracked their Credit by urging ſo many Lyes, and are not aſhamed to do ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: I ask theſe men, Did their Brother, a Friend, ſee me bring him into the Meeting, whom you ſay I did ſo much hug and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace? ſurely nay, he dares not ſay ſo: Then till you can prove that, your <hi>Charge</hi> ſtill remains falſe, and you falſe Accuſers; and how you will clear your ſelves of this, I know not.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>And ſince is a great Frequenter of his Houſe and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, as if it were a ſmall thing to wrap himſelf in all his iniquities, and ſo draw upon himſelf the vengeance due unto ſuch vile Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; contrary expreſly unto the Lords Commands, Say not a Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy; and, Have no fellowſhip with unfruitful Works of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whether it be for want of more Matter, or of more Wiſdom, I know not what their Reaſon ſhould be, that they ſhould ſtuff up their <hi>Charge</hi> with ſo many Tautologies, and ſpend ſo much time and Paper in Repetitions: The firſt part being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, I ſhall not reply again thereunto, unleſs I could do it without any prejudice to them or my ſelf in it; and ſurely if they rightly underſtood themſelves, they would never urge that from me, which will do us both no good: A Word to the Wiſe is enough.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They ſay, <hi>As if it were a ſmall thing to wrap himſelf in all his iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> They had taken a very good courſe if they had in the firſt place proved what I had done had been a ſin, and after they had ſo done, layed down before me the aggravations thereof, then it is poſſible they might have done ſomething: but for them to ſpeak at this rate, to make me a wonder as I walk up and down the ſtreets, both in City and Countrey, and the Table-talk both of Profeſſors and others, and yet never prove what they have ſaid againſt me; It is ſuch a thing that if the Lord had not kept me by his mighty Power and out-ſtretched Arm, I might have wrapt my ſelf up in my own Blood, before this time; and then whoſe Iniquity would that have been? or whoſe Door would my Blood have lain at? Take it into conſideration.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>And ſo draw upon himſelf vengeance due for ſuch tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:105462:17"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Such as have their eyes open may plainly ſee, that theſe perſons that have taken upon them to charge their Elder with ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, are greatly beſides the matter; to threaten him with <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,</hi> before they have proved he hath tranſgreſſed in that Caſe; may not theſe perſons rather think, that the vengeance of God may not ſuffer them to live, if they do not with all ſpeed repent, for to ſcandalize their Preacher, and render him to the world as an odious perſon, a <hi>Trappan,</hi> and never prove it ſo to be, but rather at laſt when they have taken it into further conſideration, ſhift the matter, thinking to come off with ſurmiſing Suppoſitions. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be not for to wrap up themſelves in their Iniquity, and draw the vengeance of God upon their own heads, let the Lord judge between us.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Contrarily expreſly unto the Lords Command, Say not a Confederacy, and have no fellowſhip, ſaith our Apoſtle, with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful works of Darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> As to the word <hi>Confederacy,</hi> I have already proved there was no ſuch thing; Therefore over-looking their Tautologie, I ſhall paſs it by: As to the <hi>unfruitful works of Darkneſs,</hi> which if they did but underſtand what they ſay, tends to one and the ſame thing; but to it I anſwer truly, as to the time of my ſociety with the perſon they mention, I muſt needs ſpeak the truth, we were ſo far from exerciſing the works of Darkneſs, that we ſpent moſt of our time in the Work of the Goſpel: Therefore as to this branch of their Charge, there is little in it that requires any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; for I abſolutely believe, if they could have charged <hi>any works of Darkneſs</hi> upon me, they would not by any means have hid them.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, They urge <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. <hi>When thou ſawest a Thief, thou conſentedſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> They may more properly preſs this to ſuch as are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions for ſuch kind of Perſons, for I do as little frequent their companies, I bleſs the Lord, as themſelves.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, And as for that they ſay, <hi>Is more conſiderable, which o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of his Abettors and Adherents told them, he did that he did to ſave herſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> What conſiderable thing there is in this I ſee not, that it ſhould to much make for their advantage; for they run away alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether from the thing in hand; and again I query with theſe men
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105462:18"/>whether theſe words were not ſpoken after the day they had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained their purpoſe upon me? If ſo, as it can be proved, then it is leſs conſiderable than any thing they have yet named: for that they brag of as conſiderable, as if they had conquered the day, appears to their great diſgrace, and this ſpeaks forth their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and deceit, to crowd that into their pretended <hi>Charge,</hi> after they had in their own will condemned me, and as they ſay (though ignorantly) <hi>caſt me out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus all men may ſee they will do ſtrange things to make their own Tale good, and when they have done all they can by patch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and piecing of things together, muſt be forced to come ſhort of a compleat <hi>Charge,</hi> without ſufficient witneſs, which to ſpeak properly is no <hi>Charge</hi> at all.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Par.</hi> The former part of this Particular I forbear to mention; not but that I can, bleſſed be the Lord, clear my ſelf of the ſtain they have put upon me in it, foraſmuch as the things contained therein, I know can never be proved: I muſt have reſpect to the day in which we live.</p>
            <p>Through Grace I do much adore the <hi>approaching of the annointed King</hi> whom they mention, and ſhould be ſorry if I ſhould be found to <hi>reproach his glorious Footſteps,</hi> as they ſay. 'Tis no ſtrange thing for them to beſpatter me in this kinde; I being acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from whence it proceeds, namely from the ſpirit of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, ſhall leave the matter in controverſie unto the Lord, who in his due time will hear the cry of the Innocent; and bleſſed be my God, I can ſay with the Noble Apoſtle, <hi>I am free from the blood of all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas they ſay, <hi>He hath given the lye unto his own Vows and Proteſtations in the ſight of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here is a miſtake: Therefore let my Accuſers recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect their memories: This I do remember I did ſay to one whoſe Name is not to this Charge, which I wonder at, who was the firſt Inſtrument that begat this Diſcord amongſt the Brethren, the Lord lay it not to her charge; I did once ſay, <hi>That I ſhould be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful how I came into his company;</hi> but as to Vows and Proteſtations I do not remember any ſuch thing, and therefore was in no capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to give the Lye to that which was not: Here I ſhall give a caution to them as well as my ſelf, Let us not be too confident in this, which was done long ago; our memories may fail us both.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:105462:18"/>
            <p> They aſſert, I ſhould ſay, <hi>I abhor the thoughts of looking towards too much ſelf, with aſſociating with ſuch perſons, and yet now tell a Brother, He was ſorry for what of that kind he had ſpoken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Of a truth, it is ſuch petty matter, I am aſhamed it ſhould come to publick view, yet being forced thereunto by the obſtinacy of theſe perſons, they being not willing to walk accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Goſpel-Rule, have ſent their reports a flying, ſo that the Wound is very great, and the Remedy muſt be anſwerable to the Diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>To the thing in hand, wherefore do they blame me in preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my ſelf, to the hurt of none? we will ſee into the Word of God if I am worthy of their blame; if we look therein, we ſhall find ſelf-preſervation ſometimes very lawful, as you may ſee in the Caſe,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Of <hi>Abraham,</hi> which expoſed his Wife to Adultery with <hi>Abimelech,</hi> to ſave himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, David</hi> ran into the Cave of <hi>Adulam,</hi> to ſave himſelf from <hi>Saul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Our Lord himſelf, when he was hunted and threatned by the <hi>Jews,</hi> removes from <hi>Jury,</hi> and walks to another place, to ſave himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, Paul</hi> the great Apoſtle of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> was let down in a Basket to ſave himſelf.</p>
            <p>Have we ſuch a cloud of Witneſſes? and many more of the Servants of Chriſt beſides Chriſt himſelf, that did uſe means to ſave themſelves, and will theſe people bring it as a Charge againſt me? Hear you may ſee the inſufficiency of their Charge.</p>
            <p>And as to the Word, <hi>Sorrow for what to a Brother I had ſpoken,</hi> will they bring it as a Charge againſt me for ſo doing, having ſome juſt ground for what I did? To tell you the truth, I had ſome jealouſie upon me concerning a perſon, as theſe perſons have had jealouſie upon them concerning my ſelf; and to deal ingenuouſly, when I was convinced I had no juſt grounds of jealouſie, I was ſorry for the ſame, and ſo ſhould they; for I appeal to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of theſe men, whether they have any juſt grounds to be thus reporting of me for a <hi>Trappan,</hi> if not, let jealouſie no more remain, for it is that fire that will burn up all love; and they will do well to try whether it has not burnt up all that tender affection which once they had to me.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:105462:19"/>
            <p> Oh Friends! I ſay to you all, yet notwithſtanding, though there hath ſuch a great cry paſt through this Nation about <hi>S. Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi>'s being ſuch a perſon, and it is found a <hi>Bradley,</hi> though not the ſame, (a man to my knowledge I never ſaw in all my life) and as it hath been proved altogether; what Reaſon can be given that their loves ſhould not be renewed again.</p>
            <p>Oh how ſhould I rejoyce to ſee that day! ſeeing it is ſo, be ingenuous to acknowledge your fault, with ſorrow and grief of heart, conſidering how God's Name and Truth hath been greatly reproached, the Work of Converſion ſtopped, the hearts of many of the Pretious Sons of <hi>Sion</hi> grieved, and all by your means; bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>zing through the Nation that which you ſee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be proved, but at laſt is found to be a miſtake, as if there were no more of that name but my ſelf; So that hitherto your pretended Charge appears to be none but a heap of untruths and ſcandals.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>He ſtands guilty of opening the nakedneſs and dealings in the Church-ſecrets in his publick preaching.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Theſe following Particulars are diſtinct from the former; They are things raked up and put together, to fill up the number. Theſe things at the firſt ſight ſeems to bear weight, but when they are examined, there is no ſuch matter.</p>
            <p>Now I muſt confeſs I am much grieved that they have put me ſo unvoidably upon it, to rake up old Matters, and muſt be forced to bring thoſe things forth to publick view, that will render thoſe perſons to be unſound, not being able to bear with ſound Doctrine. Though they have committed this folly to publick view, I will promiſe to favour them as much as I can; for though they have not ſo much love left in this ſtorm, <hi>the Accuſer of the Brethren</hi> hath raiſed, to cover their Paſtors infirmities; They ſhall ſee I have ſome left in me to cover much of theirs; and ſeeing they have brought me upon the publick Stage, I muſt be forc't to give ſome reply, though ſhort.</p>
            <p>I muſt needs ſay, to the grief of my heart, I could not Preach to any Soul-ſearching-matter, but ſhould be accuſed by one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yea, though I have laid my matter down in general terms, being willing, ſo far as I could, as it ſtood-with a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to give as little offence as I might; but let me be as careful in this matter, as was approveable in the ſight of God, yet ſome or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105462:19"/>other of them would ſtill be offended; that for a quarter of a year together and more, before they had made this Breach, <hi>I was ſo burthenſom,</hi> as they called it, <hi>in my Miniſtry, that it could not be borne by them;</hi> when ſome being offended came to tell me, <hi>that I ſpoke unto them.</hi> My anſwer to ſuch was, If they could experience what I ſaid, it was to them; and this they call <hi>the Secrets of the Church.</hi> This Particular, and my brief reply; I ſhall leave it to my Brethren in the Miniſtry for to conſider whether I was blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy in this matter.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>That it was frequently deſired by two brethren, to forbear ſuch paſſages, ſhewing how diſhonourable they were to God, and griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to them, he ſolemnly engaged never to do the like again; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs at the very next Meeting he had of his own appointing, (of which he had two or three a week beſides the Church-Meetings) he did pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly declare that his Church did ſtop his mouth, ſo that he durſt not for diſpleaſing of them preach thoſe truths he would.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Whether this be a fair way of dealing, let ſuch as are truly godly be judge in this Caſe, for theſe Perſons to ſpeak at this rate: After all breaches and differences were made up and forgotten, and were ſweetly reconciled together, and with a joynt conſent had ſat down at the Table of the Lord, in a Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Goſpel manner; and they to ſend forth their Preacher with a Letter of Recommendation to the Churches of Chriſt throughout the Nation, according to the order aforeſaid; and yet of a ſudden, in eight or nine dayes time, ſuch a ſcroul as this ſhould be drawn up againſt him, and ſpread through the Nation, and never come unto the ſight of their Paſtor, till a twelve-month after, is ſuch a wonder to me, that the like was never ſeen or heard of ſince the Creation of the World; but as touching the Brethrens deſire, to the beſt of my remembrance it was accompliſhed, they manifeſting themſelves to be very apt for to quarrel at every turn with me, and to be falling out; for peace-ſake I yielded to ſuch a thing, bearing with their weakneſs, who would indeed be often doing amiſs, and found out of the Goſpel way, but could not bear to be reproved for it; yea I ſay, for their peace ſake I yielded to their deſires, with grief of Soul I declare it, in maintaining of their peace, I broak my own, in tying up my ſelf from making improvement of my Miniſtry, and exerciſing part of that power I had received from the Lord, <hi>to reprove,</hi> as well as <hi>to exhort and comfort;</hi> it is no
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105462:20"/>ſmall trouble to me, that they force me to rip up their weakneſs at this rate, in ſuch a publick way, which now cannot be well avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they having publiſhed my Charge abroad: For Truth's ſake I muſt ſpeak a little, though nothing nigh to what I could relate; but this that <hi>I</hi> have done, is not to render them odious, as they have done their Paſtor, but rather that the Truth might appear on my part, that ſo things may be compared together, both what <hi>I</hi> can ſay for my ſelf, as well as what they have writ againſt me; or elſe who can be a true and competent Judge in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in controverſie?</p>
            <p>Seeing I am thus put upon it, I muſt ſpeak, though its poſſible I may be blamed when I have done, but all things conſidered not blame-worthy it's like in this matter: I being by the Lord and them appointed their Overſeer, and perceiving (to my grief of heart) a general neglect of the aſſembling of the Saints, and other things, did reprove this fault in general, it being a general Miſcarriage; and what? muſt I come under dealing for it? and this brought as a Charge againſt me? Surely when the Churches come to hear thereof, and the Miniſtry too, they will rather pity me than otherwiſe, and have ſome Bowels of Compaſſion to me: For me to be thrown out as an uſeleſs perſon, when I was found in the way of my duty, and reported up and down for a dangerous perſon, when it cannot be proved ſo, and to ſhift off the buſineſs think no way like this, to make their Paſtor to be thought odious by the Churches, and for them bragging when they have done, to ſay, <hi>None of the Churches own him!</hi> And this is the beſt Proof they have yet produced againſt their Paſtor. See the baſeneſs of theſe preceedings: Firſt to broach abroad that their Paſtor is a <hi>Trappan,</hi> and put a fear upon all the Churches, that none dare come at him to know what is the matter, for fear of being trappan'd; and then to give it out as if they had won the day, <hi>Oh! None of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches owns him!</hi> Let theſe men remember the Day of Judgement is at hand, in which my Cauſe will be called over, then I ſhall have a fair hearing, and true judgement in the caſe ſhall be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and then it ſhall be known who is the Offender, whether <hi>S. B.</hi> or his Accuſers. May not this People take ſhame unto themſelves, to carry themſelves ſo that they are worthy of reproof, and when they are reproved cannot bear therewith, but make en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to ſtop the mouth of their Preacher from reproving? One
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105462:20"/>would have thought they ſhould <hi>have hearkened to reproof,</hi> Prov. 13.18, 19, 25. <hi>it being the onely way to gain honour, and that they might have learn'd knowledge by it.</hi> If I may query a little with them, <hi>Have they not ſcorned Reproof,</hi> and their Paſtor got a blot thereby? O that they would well conſider the words of the Wiſe Man, <hi>He that hateth reproof ſhall die:</hi> and forget not what he farther ſays, <hi>Pro.</hi> 9.8. <hi>Reprove not a Scorner, leſt he hate thee: Rebuke a Wiſe Man, &amp; he will love thee.</hi> Let theſe Perſons conſider what they have done: If I had failed in this point, what reaſon can they ſhew that it muſt be blazed about after Reconcilement; may not ſuch as are truly ſober conclude, who are out of the prejudiced minde, that what they have done was more in malice than true love? but this is altogether off from the thing for which they made their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to bring me <hi>under dealing,</hi> as they call it, though no ſuch thing, as was falſely aſſerted, and afterward immediately denied by <hi>B. M.</hi> namely for being a <hi>Trappan:</hi> So that their pretended <hi>Charge</hi> is come to nothing at laſt, and is proved no <hi>Charge</hi> at all.</p>
            <p>Their laſt Particular I ſhall anſwer unto, containing ſeveral Branches.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>He is guilty of raſh Paſſion and ſpiritual Pride in his carria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges towards <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s in communication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I muſt acknowledge that I am not without perſonal of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, which doth adminiſter matter of true humbling and lying low at the foot of Chriſt: May it not be apprehended that for want of a right Spirit of Judgement and Brotherly Love, they may call that Paſſion, which God may approve on as true Zeal: if all things were conſidered from firſt to laſt, it may upon true grounds be gathered that they are miſtaken in this their raſh Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and while they judge their Paſtor, they are guilty of the ſame ſin, and beſpatter him in the notion of paſſion and ſpiritual pride out of a prejudiced ſpirit they have took up againſt him of a ſudden. In their Letter of Recommendation they ſent abroad to the Churches, they write no ſuch thing, it is much to me that in eight or nine days time they ſhould change their note at this rate; firſt for to cry me up, and then with all ſpeed cry me down: Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prejudices be not the Engine that ſpurts out this dirty Water of Reproach upon me, I leave the clear-ſighted Chriſtian to judge.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:105462:21"/>
            <p> Secondly, <hi>[And to vindicate a ſcandalous Tranſgreſſor, that was for to be dealt with by the Church.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It will prove to theſe perſons great advantage, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me at this rate in matters that were buried long ago, and forgotten by me, and promiſed ſo to be by them; I ſay again, It will prove for their advantage in the great Day of the Lord, if they can clear themſelves from ſlandering of their Paſtor: and were this true what they ſay, how comes it to paſs that we have very often met together at the Table of the Lord; and how is it that they have not proved faithful (if it be true what they aſſert) in this matter to the Lord and my Soul, to ſuffer me, as they ſay, a Lyar, to be their Adminiſtrator in theſe weighty Affairs in the Houſe of God? Is not this their proceedings much like unto that of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that quarrel and fall out one with another, and in revenge call over things done in times paſt, and hit them in the teeth with it? Have not theſe done even ſo, to fall upon upbraiding their Paſtor of things done long ago? Put caſe <hi>I</hi> had offended in what <hi>I</hi> had then done, how far ſhort do theſe People come of the Rule of Chriſt? let them conſider <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.32. <hi>As God for Chriſts ſake forgave us, ſo ought we to forgive one another:</hi> but inſtead of forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, how are they upbraiding! O ſhould not theſe things ſet out hearts a bleeding! that theſe perſons ſhould rake up thoſe things that were dead and buried long ago!</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They ſay, <hi>He charged a Siſter raſhly in the face of the Church, and to colour his evil made it a miſtake to juſtifie the wicked and condemn the righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this <hi>I</hi> anſwer: What I ſpake then was no more, nor ſcarce ſo much, as a Siſter of the Congregation aſſerted, and ſaid ſhe would undertake to prove it; the buſineſs that was in controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie <hi>I</hi> acquainted the Church with, when the perſon fore-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed began to ſpeak, (whether it was by her being over-powered by ſome which would have born a ſway, (and have occaſioned all theſe diſtractions amongſt us) though it did not ſo become them to do) I leave it to the Lord to judge whether ſhe was not over-powered by words and other things, to which <hi>I</hi> ſhall not ſpeak at large, leſt <hi>I</hi> make their nakedneſs too much appear: I then did declare it was found a miſtake; for me to ſay ſo, was this to cover my evil, and <hi>to juſtifie,</hi> as they term it, <hi>the wicked?</hi> was their Siſter, whom they had communion with at that time, a wicked
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105462:21"/>Perſon? how did they dare to have any communion with her then? and <hi>to condemn the Godly:</hi> but who it was I condemned they have not named, and who it is I ſhould condemn, I know not: <hi>I</hi> ſhall not judge them that do thus falſely accuſe me; neither would <hi>I</hi> have them judge me in this matter, but leave it to him which judgeth righteouſly.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>It was but few Weeks but ſome or other would meet with their wounding and burdens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the Word of the Lord did at any time wound them, let me tell them, Gods wounding tends to healing; but as to any thing elſe, I muſt profeſs my ſelf altogether a ſtranger to it: for <hi>I</hi> was, if <hi>I</hi> may ſpeak without offence, ſo far from wounding or burdening them, that I did chuſe rather to be wounded or burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my ſelf; the Lord is my Witneſs in this matter: I ſay unto this People, Doth it not rather plainly appear that their Paſtor was wounded and burdened by them, they being ſo apt to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with Goſpel-Reproofs? Yea, ſure they have done more than wounded and burdened their Paſtor, for to deprive him of his good Name under the Notion of a <hi>Trappan,</hi> when there was no ſuch thing; what will this amount to if ſtrictly enquired into and rightly judged? ſure murder in ſome kind: The Lord give them a true ſight of their evil, and then I ſhall rejoyce.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>We met with Repulſes in our Addreſs to him; You muſt not teach your Elder: Sometimes he ſcorned to be taught his Duty by any Member in the Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> True it is, when ſome of them came, as divers times they did, <hi>back-biting</hi> of ſome of their fellow-Members, whereof ſome made it their common practice ſo to do, which became a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy burden to me; and when they came to me with their ſtories, truly they had but little encouragement; and I do perceive this is that they call <hi>Repulſes;</hi> for it was my manner firſt mildly to ſhew them their evil, and then to inform them of their Duty in that concernment: but finding ſtill ſome who made it their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to go from houſe to houſe, carrying Tales, which ſince have been inſtrumental to bring their private diſorderly walking into a publick diſorder alſo; witneſs the noiſe their proceedings have made throughout all the Churches; I perceiving mild Inſtruction would not reclaim them. <hi>I</hi> was fain to uſe ſharpneſs; which they ignorantly call <hi>raſh Paſſion, I</hi> not anſwering the expectation of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105462:22"/>ſome in this kinde, but reproving them ſharply for the ſame, they have been pleaſed to terme it, <hi>Spiritual Pride:</hi> But why ſhould I or any other think this ſtrange? for <hi>Paul</hi> the Noble Apoſtle of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> was judged by the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.3. <hi>And counts it but a ſmall thing to be ſo judged;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall I, for what I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one in this kind, hath been in a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſcharge of my duty, though I have purchaſed to my ſelf a blot for my labour; I truſt the Lord will enable me to wear it as my Crown, what ever ſpecious pretences they may have to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me odious to the People of God; they carrying of it at ſuch a rate, to make the Churches believe that they have dealt with me in an orderly way, when it is no ſuch thing, cauſing ſome to ſay, <hi>His own Church hath dealt with him and caſt him out,</hi> when they were not in a capacity ſo to do, being under dealing at that time themſelves, by their Paſtor and others of the Church, for their rebellion againſt the Righteous Laws and inſtituted Orders of Chriſt's Houſe: What they have unrighteouſly done, hath ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hitherto to carry the day, as if they had obtained a victory, and cryed it up ſo, before the matter came to tryal: But it muſt paſs for truth right or wrong: why ſo? there is no good reaſon can be ſhewed for it I am ſure: ſome ſay, <hi>Becauſe the Church hath caſt him out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſhall ſpeak in the Language of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.5. <hi>Your Brethren that hated you, that caſt you out for my Names ſake, ſaying, Let the Lord be glorified; but he ſhall appear to your joy, and they ſhall be aſhamed:</hi> And for all their bold aſſertion, that <hi>I am not willing to hearken to the leaſt Member of the Church, to hear what they can ſay;</hi> I hope I ſhall make it appear, that I am not only willing to hearken, but to learn of them too, if I find them in a capacity to teach.</p>
            <p>Theſe people, all men may ſee by their carriage to me, were ſo far from being able to teach me my duty, that they had not learnt to practiſe their own; it doth plainly appear they judged me without a cauſe.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>Sometimes he would incompaſs us with fained flatteries and repentances, and yet in the mean time break forth into thoſe foul breaking parts, that indeed he was become a burthen to us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer; What they mean by <hi>feigned flatteries,</hi> I am yet to learn; then very unlikely to compaſs them about therewith:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105462:22"/>Surely theſe people, <hi>Have bent their Tongues like their Bow for lies,</hi> Jer: 9.3. And we may ſay of them as the Prophet of old did, <hi>They proceed from evil to evil.</hi> If by <hi>fained flattery</hi> they mean my ready condeſcention to them of low degree, in denying my ſelf, as often I did, in having better thoughts of them than I had of my ſelf, I making of it my work to maintain the peace of the Church; if this be their meaning, I muſt needs confeſs my ſelf guilty; but as to any thing elſe, I am a ſtranger to it: Therefore that which they call <hi>fained flattery,</hi> is a Paradox to me: And the thing they term by the name of <hi>Repentances,</hi> I do as little under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand as the former; unleſs it be thus, if at any time I had ſpoken that which through their weakneſs, being petriſh Children, and ſoon offended at reproof, (though they had need enough of it, and as they truly confeſs to me in their Letter they writ when I was a Priſoner in <hi>Newgate,</hi> That <hi>they were Children in the Matters and Affairs of the Church, and need be taught</hi>) then I would expreſs my trouble in this caſe, that I was ſuch an Offence to them; they being in the <hi>high minde,</hi> when they ſhould come down into the <hi>godly fear,</hi> being apt to be ſelf-conceited: and muſt I be reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for this my Love and Tenderneſs to them? I truſt my God will enable me to bear it, though that which makes it the harder, is, Becauſe it is from the Houſe of my Friends, and them that have been and ſtill are as dear to me as my own Life, though they have thus dealt by me, and I <hi>am become to them as a dead man out of mind.</hi> If theſe be the things that made them cry out of being burdened, let all ſober men judge whether they had any juſt cauſe for it: May it not truely be otherwiſe applied more ſafely, That theſe things could not but prove a burden to their Paſtor?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> ſhall omit one thing in this Particular, it being ſuch nonſenſe that <hi>I</hi> underſtand it not, and ſhall paſs to the next thing in their pretended <hi>Charge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>Some of thoſe petty things we have alſo at large, for to be brought forth, if deſired by any.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Were it not to encourage theſe people to come under the breach of their ſolemn Covenant they made when they enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Church-Communion, not to rip up matters in this kinde, I ſhould ſay then, By all means bring them forth, that the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and others may ſee what a heavy Drudge their Paſtor hath been made by them, and how they have had no reſpect to his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105462:23"/>peace, but troubled and burdened him with ſuch matters that by their own confeſſion are counted <hi>petty Things:</hi> The Chriſtian Reader may take notice, That their <hi>Charge</hi> at the beſt, as they have declared, is but a <hi>petty Charge;</hi> the Reaſon is, The matters contained therein are but <hi>petty Things:</hi> and truly I do not much wonder they were ſo backward in letting me have a ſight thereof, it may be they were aſhamed of their work, it being but a <hi>petty Buſineſs:</hi> I muſt needs acknowledge they have given as true a Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to their Twelvemonths Labours as could be invented; and ſhould they ſit a Twelvemonth longer onely to ſtudy for a Title to ſend forth their pretended <hi>Charge</hi> into the World, they could not chooſe one that would be more fitting. Now Friends, See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it hath appeared to be ſuch a petty Buſineſs, I hope your poor oppreſſed Paſtor will be reſtored to his Birthright again, that is to ſay, <hi>His Good Name,</hi> that hath by your means been taken from him; for <hi>a Good Name is better than precious Oyntment, Eccleſ.</hi> 7.1. which you have ſtained by your ſcandalous Reports, ſpread by your means up and down the Land of my Nativity; but if you will not, yet it ſhall work for my good and your hurt in the Day of Judgement. Sure all men that have but the leaſt ſpark of Grace, will ſay it is but a reaſonable thing, ſeeing all this cry and ſtir about <hi>Samuel Bradley</hi> doth at laſt appear to be but a <hi>petty Report,</hi> and could never to this day be made otherwiſe to appear; for the moſt credible perſons that ever had a hand to ſpread it abroad, which have gone under the name of very good Chriſtians, neither did nor can ſpeak any thing of their own knowledge: then it remains to be but a <hi>petty Report</hi> ſtill. And when theſe perſons have been asked, <hi>Upon what grounds do you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port this of the Perſon aforeſaid?</hi> their anſwer has been, <hi>His Church has cast him out upon this very Account:</hi> and now that which they have called all this while a <hi>Church Act,</hi> though they had no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo to do, is found to be at the beſt but a <hi>petty Surmiſe</hi> or Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: What? and no more? No truly: Then, away, ſaith the ſober-minded Chriſtian, with this <hi>petty Charge;</hi> for in open <hi>Court</hi> it is condemned: and let their Paſtor's Good Name be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, <hi>While we were dealing with him, at one time, breaking forth into a wicked reviling and contempt; as, He had brought up a Bird to pick out his Eyes: A Brother that then ſpake, called him
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105462:23"/>Black-mouth, Foul-mouth, he had ſpit the Devil all Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As touching the Bird they mention, of all the things I did ſpeak, <hi>that</hi> I cannot remember: however it may be reliſhed, yet in one ſence it is undeniably true: for this man whom they make mention of, was he that for two or three hours together did revile me in ſuch a ſhameful manner, that ſome there preſent, although they were not Members, yet conſcientious Perſons, were ſo much grieved, they had much ado to continue in the hearing of him; his ſpeaking was in ſuch an unchriſtian-like manner, that ſome there preſent ſaid, <hi>He did act and lock as if he had been the very Picture of Envy;</hi> and he ſpake with ſuch rage that to ſomes perceivance he looked black in the mouth; then I pray conſider, was that to revile him, when I ſpake nothing but the truth concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him? And put caſe theſe kinde of proceedings and great op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, had ſo much prevailed with me, that I had ſpake worſe than all this; who was the cauſe of it? were not thoſe perſons that would not let me have the ſame liberty that a Malefactor or a Murderer ſhall have at the Bar, that is to ſpeak what he can for himſelf, before he be ſentenced to death? but I muſt have my Sentence before <hi>I</hi> could be heard: <hi>Oppreſſion will make a wiſe man mad.</hi>—And did I revile him to call him Foul-mouth, when he had ſuch foul Expreſſions flowing from him, that were not becoming him? and whether he did not act the part of the Devil all the day, let the wiſe man judge, who accuſed his Paſtor in the face of all there preſent, and yet could not, when he was put upon it, prove what he ſaid; for we all know that <hi>the Devil is the Accuſer of the Brethren,</hi> Rev. 12.10. then you may plainly ſee I did not wrong him in the leaſt, to ſay he <hi>ſpit the Devil all day,</hi> when he ſpit forth his venom of malice, that he was beyond the bounds of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
            <p>Now if they had any regard to God's Glory and their own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, they ſhould not have laid open their weakneſs abroad, thinking to let the nakedneſs of their Paſtor be ſeen to all men, and thereby have made manifeſt their own ſhame: ſuppoſe I had acted all that which <hi>B. M.</hi> had falſely aſſerted, was there no other courſe for them to deal with me, than to make me odious before all, ere they had examined the cauſe, to ſee whether I had deſerved ſuch things at their hands? But it doth appear this man with ſome others had a deſign to carry on, and he thought the way to make ſure work
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105462:24"/>of it was to ſtop his Paſtors Mouth, for fear he ſhould ſpoile his deſign; for he with ſome others, were reſolved upon the matter to cut him off right or wrong, and with all expedition too; and had forgot to go to prayer firſt. A Member that was there preſent, which wept bitterly to ſee their proceedings, ſeeing of them ſo nimble at the work, bad them conſider what they did, for it was not a buſineſs of ſmall concernment to cut off an Elder; to which ſome replied, <hi>Well then, we will go and ſeek God:</hi> the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that prayed, was very ingenious to confeſs (though he was one of them in the cutting-off deſign, <hi>John Johnſon</hi> by name) he had no anſwer at all: with that <hi>Benjamin Minzes</hi> did go to pray, to ſee if he could have an anſwer, as we may ſo gather by the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; and after he had done, he was anſwered, as he did ſay, from <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.20. <hi>I have a few things againſt thee, becauſe thou ſuffereſt that Woman</hi> Jezebel, <hi>which calleth her ſelf a Propheteſs, to teach, and Seduce my Servants to commit Fornication, and to eat things Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed unto Idols:</hi> Whether this was a pertinent anſwer, or any anſwer at all, we ſhall certainly know at the Judgement Day, which haſtens: and upon this they ſpeedily proceeded, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to let it ſlip till another day of meeting, though it was deſired by one of the Brethren, and alſo by them granted, yet this <hi>B.M.</hi> was ſo eager in the matter, and did ſo much prevail upon them, that he cauſed the reſt of his adherents to breake their ſolemn Promiſe, which they made to the aforeſaid Brother; <hi>B. M.</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried it with theſe words, as can be proved to his face, <hi>That if they did not do it then, they ſhould not do it at all.</hi> If they had not a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter intent to propagate their Murdering Deſign, to ſlay the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, rather than to keep to the juſt known ſtanding Rule of Chriſt, let him that is of underſtanding in this matter, appear to be judge in this caſe; and what was all this, but to carry on the work of the Devil all the day? and by theſe things have made me a wonder to many; yet God is my ſtrong refuge, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.7.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, <hi>Verily ſcoffing at the Work of the Lord; being acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he ſhould be cut off, ſcoffingly ſaid to one of his adherents, It would be cut and dryed by and by.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer; O how have theſe perſons addicted themſelves to ſpeak that which is not true! for let my Reply be conſidered, whether it was a Scoff, when I underſtood their determination what they was reſolved to do; as it were informed upon good and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105462:24"/>ſufficient proof, that ſome of them were reſolved the breach ſhould not be made up; and by their management of things, I ſaw their deſign plainly tending unto the ſame: When they did threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to cut me off, I ſoberly anſwered, <hi>It was ready cut and dryed;</hi> that is, to ſpeak after the ſmilitude, it was ready done to their hands: how and which way they will make this a Scoff, I know not, unleſs they wreſt my words, and take them in the wrong ſence: Let theſe men remember, the ſame meaſure they mete forth to me, ſhall be meted to them again.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, <hi>As a further Evidence of his Hardneſs and Implacable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs under all, when it was told him he was cut off, he makes that the time of his liberty to preach the Goſpel unto the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here they have uttered words without knowledge, to tell the People, that it is an evidence of his hardneſs, what, <hi>to rejoyce in a time of Liberty to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt?</hi> here have they diſcovered their blindneſs and ignorance abundantly, to ſay, <hi>it was an evidence of his Implacableneſs:</hi> It is very plain by what they aſſert <hi>they know not what they ſay, nor whereof they affirm. Firſt,</hi> The word <hi>Implacableneſs,</hi> implies, Unappeaſable; a thing quite contrary to their aſſertion; whoſe malice admits of no terms of Reconciliation. Now let the Reader conſider whether this raſh Cenſure which they have ignorantly caſt upon me, hath not fallen upon themſelves, who would by no means admit of Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, though the terms thereof have been tendered to them, as aforeſaid was proved; ſo that I may ſay unto them, <hi>therefore thou art inexcuſable, O man, whoſoever thou art that judgeſt; for wherein thou judgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf; for thou that judgeſt, doſt the ſame things: how do they think that continue in ſo doing, to eſcape the Judgements of God? Rom.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Implacableneſs,</hi> doth import haters of Peace, and ſuch who are wholly for war: ſo that out of their own mouth, they are condemned; for they are ſo far from peace, that they have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed open War through the Nation againſt their Paſtor, though without juſt cauſe, that a man can ſcarce go into any part thereof, but he ſhall hear the report of this their unrighteous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, Implacableneſs,</hi> doth alſo import to us, ſuch as will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be reconciled or pacified, when they are once moved, and have taken any quarrel in hand, ſuch as are irreconcilable, without
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105462:25"/>friendſhip or peace, who being once offended, will never be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled more, neither will admit of any League or Covenant; witneſs the Continuation of their reproach and ſlanders; that let theſe men or women come into any company, whether Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans or others, as can be proved againſt ſome of them to their great ſhame (not at all regarding the Glory of God) will fall a Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Backbiting and Slandring of their Paſtor, as if they were ſo hungerly bitten, that they can not tell when they have done enough, or ſhould never be ſatisfied or take their revenge of him: This is <hi>Implacableneſs</hi> indeed; the fire of their wrath being once kindled, they carry it on at ſuch a rate, as if they would never let it go out, till they hurried me out of breath, or hunted their Paſtor to death, altogether refuſing to ſhew any kind of friendſhip to him in the leaſt; and being not contented to uſe him ſo vilely themſelves, but uſe all endeavours that poſſible may be, to bring up all others to the ſame <hi>[Implacableneſs.]</hi> O this is Perſecution with a witneſs! And when they do hear of any Perſon of Quality that doth come to hear the ſaid <hi>S. B.</hi> ſome of them make it their work to run to their houſes, and back-bite him extreamly, with ſuch-like expreſſions, <hi>He is a wicked dangerous perſon;</hi> though when they have been asked by ſober perſons, whether they ſpeak of their own knowledge? have told them, <hi>No;</hi> but it is true enough, you need not queſtion it: Why? <hi>O I had it from a gratious Soul that would not lie:</hi> and if you come to that gratious Soul, if you can find him out, ask him, Do you know this and that to be true of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Bradley? Not of my own knowledge, but from one, whom I am ſure will not dare for to tell a lie:</hi> So you ſhall at laſt when it comes to the iſſue, find it comes from his own Church; and examine them of his own Church, Do any of you know <hi>S. B.</hi> your Paſtor, to be a Trappan? <hi>No, but we ſurmiſe or ſuppoſe ſome ſuch thing;</hi> ſo at laſt when we have ſearched into the bottom, there is no ſuch thing: by this means have they made perſons take it for granted, when they could never prove any ſuch thing. They never ceaſed in this way of proceeding, till they had wrought up perſons unto the ſame prejudiced mind as themſelves; and by this means have prevented many from the Means of Grace. I hope by this time they ſee their blindneſs, and do now underſtand that <hi>S. B.</hi> ſtands clear from the guilt of <hi>Implacableneſs,</hi> and it fals out to be their own portion: The Lord grant them timely repentance, and let them
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105462:25"/>learn hereafter to ſpeak the Truth, and utter ſuch things as are truth, that their ſpeech may not be condemned: for as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>Job.</hi> 34.3. <hi>As the palate taſtes meat, ſo doth the ear try words:</hi> Their words have been examined and tried from the beginning of their petty <hi>Charge,</hi> now almoſt to the end, and have been found falſe and unſound; and out of their own mouths are they caſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and found Lyars; and ſuch Perſons as theſe are not like to be competent Judges in ſuch weighty matters, and in the room of judging of others, if <hi>they would judge themſelves, they ſhould not be judged of the Lord.</hi> Theſe Perſons may do well to conſider, That God will one day ask them, <hi>Why doſt thou judge thy Brother? or why doſt thou ſet at nought thy Brother?</hi> Rom. 14.10. <hi>We ſhall all ſtand before the Judgement-Seat of God.</hi> But I ſhall paſs to the next Particular.</p>
            <p n="11">11 Par. <hi>He gives out, That he is wronged, and hath made his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the Churches, but cannot be heard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Reader may obſerve this to be a petty Charge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and this their pretended <hi>Charge</hi> hath been found falſe: for to make people believe ſtrange things of their Paſtor, and now come to wave the matter becauſe they cannot prove what they have ſaid, and put us off with a Story or a Tale about the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            <p>As touching making <hi>my Appeal,</hi> you may now ſee I have, and not onely to them but to the whole World: for the Innocent is neither aſhamed to ſhew his Face, nor his Cauſe, though they were; witneſs their under-hand-dealing for this Twelvemonth together: and now their Actions are come to Light, the Light hath manifeſted their Works are for the fire, that muſt be burnt up: and let theſe Perſons labour to carry themſelves better for the future, leſt they and their Works be burnt up together: and let them take it into conſideration, That they have put me out of a capacity of making the Churches acquainted with their Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, but in this manner; which I confeſs is not uſual, nor had it been ſo, if it had not been long of themſelves; for the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches have by their inſtigations been ſet againſt me, and have been afraid of me, though to this day I have given them no cauſe, and I hope in God ſhall never ſo do: for in the preſence of God I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my true love to them; and not onely ſo, but to the poor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed and oppreſſed Seed of God under all diſtinctions whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105462:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:105462:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:105462:27"/>ever: for through Grace I can truly ſay to this day, though I have been rendered vile and baſe, I have love to all Saints; and my condition I have related to ſome that now are eminent in the Churches, and made my moan to them, telling them of my great Burden; but what am I the better? I muſt bear my own Burden: for I ſee none ſo ready to ſearch out the Truth of the Matter, or bear the Burden with me, but a few Lambs of Chriſt, who for ſo doing are laid under Reproach, though there is none can blame their upright Converſations juſtly. By the wicked Contrivance of this back-biting People, I perceive that fear and jealouſie is got upon the hearts of all them that call themſelves by the Name of the Churches of Chriſt; I do not ſay they deſerve not that Name, but I wiſh rather they may. And ſo much as to my Appeal to the Churches.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Par. <hi>He now makes his Appeal to God, and queſtions not but in a Twelvemonth he ſhall make Us and all the Churches know their evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Can theſe men blame me for making my Appeal to God, when I came on purpoſe to make my Appeal unto them, and could not be heard? what cauſe they have to do ſo, I know not.</p>
            <p>As touching my <hi>making of them know their Evil,</hi> I might have been better than my word, had not they carried it about ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly, inſomuch that I could not obtain a ſight of my <hi>Charge</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no terms till the Twelvemonth came about; but time enough to their ſhame who work ſo ſecretly that it was a wonder, if not almoſt a miracle for me to come to the ſight of this their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Charge:</hi> but what God will have brought to Light, who can by their cunning contrivances prevent? for he is a God that will <hi>bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.5. as he hath done this, bleſſed be his Name: I have been charged upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral accounts, but never in a right capacity to make my Reply till now; and now I hope thoſe of the Churches that have joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in with them in their Work of Deceit, will ſee it to be an evil, and free themſelves again of it; ſeeing I have proved my ſelf to be no <hi>Trappan,</hi> but Innocent in the caſe, and none can prove to the contrary: and I hope ſo well of them, that they do ſee it an evil by this time, to fear a man that never did (nor never doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend) them any harm.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Par. They would make the Churches and Others believe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105462:27"/>that this <hi>is but a brief Copy of thoſe many grand Evils for which our Brethren before and now, have cut him off, and caſt him out for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Their grand Evils, as they are pleaſed to call them, are proved moſt of them (if not all) grand lyes, groundleſs Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, Surmiſings, and miſtakes: I pray what will their <hi>petty Evils,</hi> as they term them, prove, but <hi>petty lyes?</hi> if they were brought forth and to be weighed, <hi>Job</hi> 3.6, 7. <hi>In the Ballance of the Sanctuary,</hi> namely, the Ballance of Truth, they will without all doubt be found to be too light; they had need look very well about them, for all the flouriſh they have made of <hi>caſting me out for the deſtruction of the fleſh:</hi> what are their lying ſurmiſings and the like, but the works of the fleſh? Theſe perſons may do very well to ſee <hi>the Beam that is in their own eye,</hi> Mat. 7.3. then ſhall they ſee more plainly <hi>to pull out the Mote that is in their Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eye:</hi> The time may come, that God may ſay unto them and to all the reſt of their fellow-boaſters, <hi>Who hath required theſe things at your hands?</hi> Though you are pleaſed to call it <hi>the work of the Lord,</hi> take notice that <hi>backbiting</hi> and <hi>whiſpering,</hi> and <hi>falſe-accuſing,</hi> are the works of the fleſh, called ſo in Scripture, and not the works of the Lord: Therefore all men may ſee, they have more cauſe to lie low in the ſight of God for this their evil practiſe for a twelvemonth together laſt paſt, then to boaſt as they have done: So, <hi>They do but glory in their ſhame, Phil.</hi> 3.19. for theſe works are not the works of God, but their own, which muſt be burnt up; for God is coming with his ſword to cut down all that is not of his own, <hi>for with Fire and Sword will God plead with all fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that a word of Exhortation might faſten on theſe poor wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Sheep that are gone a ſtray <hi>upon the dark mountains,</hi> Jer. 13.16. that might cauſe them for to <hi>return to their firſt love, or husband, for then was it better with them then now,</hi> Hoſ. 2.7. and make haſte, leſt <hi>the Lord our God make a breach upon them, for that they ſought him not after the due order,</hi> 1 Chron. 15.13.</p>
            <p>Oh that they would repent out of hand for their heady and raſh proceedings againſt their innocent Paſtor, leſt deſtruction be their portion, notwithſtanding all their Profeſſion.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Par. <hi>And ſo do now bear our Teſtimony againſt all his Evil, and all his Adherents, and ſet our hands to the truth of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this I Anſwer, If theſe Aſſertors and Concluders did
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105462:28"/>walk like perſons indued with true knowledge; they ſhould have proved the things they talk of to be evils, before they had ſet their hands thereunto: by what they have done, they have mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted themſelves not to be wiſe nor right Artiſts at the work of accuſation.</p>
            <p>Again, if they could have proved what they have ſubſcribed unto, to be Evils, the next work had been to have layed them down before me, and made ſome endeavour to have holpen me to a ſight thereof, as well as themſelves, and ſhewn me by way of aggravation the danger of them: and if I had been obſtinate not to have heard ſome of them alone, to brought two more with them, and took ſome pains with me for to recover me out of that which they are pleaſed to call an Evil; and if I had remained in an obſtinate mind, then with ſorrow of heart and bowels of love told it to the Church, &amp; the Church to have made ſome endeavour to recover me, and if I would not have ſeen my Evil, then to have ſet a day a part for Faſting and Prayer, and to have mourned bitterly, under the conſideration of the thoughts of the loſs of a chief Pillar of the Church; and when all this work was done, then in a ſolemn reverent and godly manner, to have gone trembling at the thought of what muſt of neceſſity then have been done, ſeeing there was no avoiding of it; and conſider what was to be done af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this, not to reproach.</p>
            <p>Nay, <hi>For ſufficient to ſuch a man was this puniſhment which was inflicted upon many,</hi> 2 Cor. 2.6, 7. <hi>So that contrarywiſe, they ought rather to forgive him, and comfort him, leſt perhaps ſuch a one ſhould be ſwallowed up with overmuch ſorrow; wherefore I beſeech you that you would confirm your love towards him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay to theſe people, Was any of this done? Was the firſt ſtep taken in this work, much leſs the laſt, that was done to the ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous perſon? How may theſe people dread the thoughts of their preſent Proceedings with their former, for fear God may charge them with Spiritual murder at the Day of the Lord, in putting a ſtop to converſion-work, and cauſe Souls to ſtumble? I ſay, Oh what comfort can theſe men have, that have ſet their hand to ſuch a work as this is? The Lord give them a ſight and true ſence and ſorrow, yea true repentance of the ſame: Sure by this time they may plainly ſee, if they do not harden their hearts, that they were out of the way of the Lord; and with what comfort can they go
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105462:28"/>to the grave with this Load upon their Conſciences? or what peace they can have for theſe their irregular Proceedings, I know not? and truly it is to be admired they do not yet bluſh at that they ſtile their Teſtimony; Sure they underſtand not what they ſay: for the word <hi>Teſtimony</hi> doth ſignifie, amongſt other things, a good report from others: but this which they have done, is found to be of no good report; therefore falſely termed by them a <hi>Teſtimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, a Teſtimony doth alſo import, a witneſſing well; but they have witneſſed unto that which is Lyes, Suppoſitions and Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſings, which is very ill; therefore for to ſpeak properly, have born no Teſtimony againſt <hi>Samuel Bradley,</hi> but rather have made their ignorance further appear, and know not what they ſay in this caſe, nor what a Teſtimony is; and yet theſe perſons will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take for to paſs Sentence of Excommunication upon their Paſtor, and that as ſoon as his back was turned from them was it done, but never to his face.</p>
            <p>And whereas they ſeem to reflect upon the reſt of their Fellow-Members, which bore a better Conſcience than themſelves, which they call, <hi>Adherents;</hi> they have little cauſe ſo to do; for they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Rules of Chriſt better, than to run raſhly and headily upon things contrary to the right Order, but have waited with patience upon the Lord, and have proved Fellow-feelers of their Paſtors Sorrows and great Afflictions, that have befallen him through the means of the perſons aforeſaid, that are turned his Accuſers, though falſely; and they in Conſcience could not joyn with them without breach of Covenant. I ſhall ſay unto theſe my Accuſers, had they been as tender of the Glory of God, as theſe they call <hi>My Adherents,</hi> they might have been made partakers of true Peace with them; though by their means they are made to ſtand alone ſeparated from the reſt of their Brethren, to their great grief; and could they violate the peace of their conſciences as thoſe have done, they might have been their dear Friends ſtill: Let theſe men be careful, leſt they ſlay the Upright in Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>with the Sword of their Mouth,</hi> namely, bitter words, as they have not been aſhamed to do, leſt Wrath break forth from the Lord upon them.</p>
            <p>And whereas they ſay, <hi>They have ſet their hands to the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ask them whether their Conſciences did not prick them when they were ſetting their Pen to Paper? ſo as they began with a lye,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:105462:29"/>they conclude with a lye alſo: O how can theſe People with confidence call that <hi>a Charge,</hi> which they themſelves confeſt in the laſt Particular thereof, to be but <hi>petty Things?</hi> or call that <hi>a Truth,</hi> which is ſtuffed up with ſo many <hi>Lyes, Suppoſitions,</hi> and <hi>ſurmiſing Expreſſions,</hi> as hath been proved all along? O that they would lay theſe ſad proceedings to heart, that for this Twelvemonth together they have contrived againſt their innocent Paſtor, as they have owned him to be, and yet have cried him up for a <hi>Trappan,</hi> at ſuch a high hand! They may ſee, if they do not wilfully ſhut their Eyes, that his Innocencie has ſo ſhined in this matter, that the Lord hath holp him to weather the ſtorms of all ſorts they have raiſed upon him, onely from Fears and Jealouſies: O what will they do, when God ſhall call them to an account! How will they be able to ſtand before him! It is not their ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of Church-Fellowſhip that will ſhelter them from the wrath of God: for if he ſet the Worm of Conſcience a gnawing, their Gourd will ſoon be deſtroyed, and where are they then? My Prayer ſhall be <hi>that they may repent,</hi> and the Lord forgive them, for I do; and for ever hereafter let them be ſilent, and never more open their mouth to reproach: and as <hi>Job</hi> ſaid of his friends, ſo ſhall I ſay of mine, <hi>Job</hi> 16.24. <hi>I have heard many ſuch things; miſerable Comforters are you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now you may ſee I have diligently examined this their pretended <hi>Charge,</hi> that hath occaſioned ſuch a ſtir in the Nation, and have found it to ſtand upon the Foundation of Untruths, Jealouſie, Tautology, groundleſs Fears, Surmiſings and Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: by which means have many been made to have hard thoughts, and to ſpeak high words againſt <hi>S. Bradley,</hi> as if he had been turned from what acquaintance he had with God, to be <hi>a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Betrayer of the Lords People,;</hi> and thorow this means alſo, for a year together, and more, have ſundry, yea, ſcores of lyes been raiſed of him, whereof many of them are upon Record, (but not judged expedient to be publiſhed) and are proved by ſufficient godly Perſons to be falſehoods; as may be ſeen by any ſober Chriſtian, that deſires to be ſatisfied therein: Though theſe things have occaſioned unexpreſſible trouble unto me; yet in the midſt of all, <hi>I do rejoyce in the teſtimony of a good Conſcience,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.12. being clear from any kinde of guilt in this matter, God is my wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105462:29"/>and in aſſarance thereof, I do in the fear and name of the Lord God everlaſting now declare to all ſorts of People, Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, or Prophane, for to come forth and accuſe me if they can, in this matter upon their own knowledge, or by poſitive proof from any, That I did ever in all my life do any thing that had the leaſt tendency to any ſuch thing, as to the inſnaring of the People of the Lord: I do here further declare in the preſence of God, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Men, as I ſhall anſwer it at the great and terrible day of the Lord, which now haſtens, That my Soul doth loath and abhor the very thoughts, much more the acting of any ſuch thing: And were not the Glory of God and the Good of poor Sinners con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in this matter, I ſhould not have put Pen to Paper, but ſtill remained in ſilence, knowing that with the help of the Lord my Innocencie in this caſe, though it may be long, would have ſtopt the mouths of the ſcandalous Reproachers; I hearing the Goſpel ſo much reproached on my part, being repreſented to the Nation to be that I am not, namely a <hi>Trappan;</hi> and Profeſſors on their parts making of it their buſineſs to broach new Lyes every Week almoſt, if not altogether, which my ſoul was ſorely grieved to hear; and this pretended Charge by ſo great a Providence brought to my hand, I could forbear no longer, judging it my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to let the Lords People through the whole Nation, underſtand the whole matter in controverſie between me and thoſe of my own Houſe, to the end they may be in a right capacity to judge between us.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord haſten the time that <hi>Sions</hi> Breaches may be made up, that there may be <hi>no more ſmoak in his holy Temple,</hi> but a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſerving of the Lord <hi>with one conſent:</hi> Which is the Prayer of him whoſe Love doth run out (however it hath been thought other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes by many) to all the precious Seed of Renown; who longs to ſee <hi>Sion</hi> a quiet Habitation, and the Joy of the whole Earth, her Children to walk in Love, and ſo fulfill the whole Law, to the end they may live in Peace. <hi>So the God of Peace be with you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To cloſe up all, I ſhall (omitting divers Letters of Vindication written in my behalf by theſe People) preſent the Reader with a true Copy, word for word, of <hi>their Letter of Recommendation,</hi> by which they ſent me forth to preach the Goſpel; which was done bur eight or nine days before this Dreadful Breach.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:105462:30"/>
            <head>The Church of Chriſt meeting together in the Faith and Order of the Goſpel, in <hi>Salisbury Lane</hi> near <hi>Redriff,</hi> Sendeth Greeting: This Letter of Recommendation, to be communicated to the Churches of Chriſt in <hi>London,</hi> or any part of the Nation; and to all Saints of the like pretious Faith with Us, whereſoever.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WE there in the Name and Fear of God in a ſolemn manner, as we do apprehend, according to the Rule of Chriſt laid down in the Goſpel, by Faſting and Prayer, ſeparated, ſet apart and ſent forth our dear Brother in the Lord</hi> Samuel Bradley, <hi>in the Work of the Miniſtry, to preach the Goſpel of Free Grace and Reconciliation to poor Sinners, and of Conſolation to Saints: To be inſtant in this Work in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon; to Reprove, Rebuke, Exhort, with all long-Suffering and Doctrine, as He ſhall have opportunity offered. We do judge Him to be one whom the Lord hath made able by his Spirit for to divide the Word of Truth aright: Being one that hath been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Terrors of the Lord, knows how the better by the Terrors of the Lord to perſwade Sinners to come in to Chriſt: And one who hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced the pangs of the New Birth, who hath Chriſt formed in Him; That hath been Inſtrumental in the Hand of the Lord to turn Us and many more from Sin to Grace, from Darkneſs to Light; And ſome, if not all of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, have been a Seal of His Miniſtry (in the Lord) and He is near and dear to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s for the Work's ſake; Whoſe Converſation is in all things becoming the Goſpel of Our Lord JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S; Whoſe Life is a conſtant Sermon to Us. Now if You account <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s Fellow-Citizens of the</hi> New Jeruſalem, <hi>and Subjects of the King of kings, and Heirs of the Kingdom of Grace, being made Partakers of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Receive Him as Our own Bowels, whom We truſt is very much upon the Heart of God, and hath obtained great Grace, who hath had large Experience of the Love of God, who is a Brother beloved, who is eſpecially known to Us, who hath begotten Us to Chriſt, who is Our Spiritual Paſtor to feed Us, and to walk in and out before Us; Therefore We may ſay of him as</hi> Paul <hi>ſaid of</hi> Timothy, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.30.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105462:30"/>We have no Man ſo dear to Us, who will naturally care for our Eſtate, <hi>&amp;c. But we know the Proof of Him, That He hath been and is a great Labourer in the Vinyard of the Lord: We ſend Him therefore forth in the Name of the Lord, to do the Work of the Lord, that when We ſee Him again, We may do it with Joy: Receive Him therefore in the Work of the Lord with all gladneſs, and hold ſuch in Reputation for Chriſts ſake, yea, and for their Work ſake. And ſo We reſt Your Brethren in Chriſt the Beloved of the Father, who is full of Grace and Truth; and ſubſcribe Our Names in the behalf of the Church. The Grace of Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with You all.</hi> (Amen.)</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>The 5th of the 5th Month, 1663.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>John Glyde, <hi>Elder.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Benj. Minzes, <hi>Deac.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>John Johnſon.</item>
                     <item>Henry Tabor.</item>
                     <item>Roger Morlie.</item>
                     <item>John Aſten.</item>
                     <item>John Bentlie.</item>
                     <item>Samuel Hackney</item>
                     <item>Jeoffry Lane.</item>
                     <item>William Green.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
